<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="52"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[INDIRA GANDHI INSTITUTE OF

                DEVELOPMENT RESEARCH







   M A Y   E D I T I O N                                        V O L U M E   0 1   |   I S S U E   0 1

              E C O N P ₹ I S M










  COVID-19: IMPACT & LESSONS LEARNT



































































                            I G I D R   S T U D E N T   N E W S L E T T E R]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[C O N T R I B U T O R S






                                              I G I D R   N E W S L E T T E R




                                        F A C U L T Y   A D V I S O R S


                                                  Bharti Nandwani
                                            Gopakumar Achuthankutty



                                                    E D I T O R S


                                          Chitralekha Sudhakar Gaikwad
                                                   Gaorima Nahata
                                                         Khushi

                                                  Medha Chatterjee
                                                      Rimi Gupta
                                                    Shrey Saurabh

                                                    Swarupjit Palit



                                               D E S I G N   T E A M


                                               Promit Kanti Chaudhuri
                                                     Shirsha Saha

                                                        Ujjawal



                                                V O L U N T E E R S


                                                 Alumni Committee
                                                    Charu Nagpal

                                                Romit Abhichandani]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[TABLE OF CONTENTS













      E D I T O R I A L   B O A R D



      M E S S A G E   C O R N E R

      • Director's Note
      • Faculty Advisors' Note




      A R T I C L E S   F R O M   E X P E R T S

          One Year of Covid-19 and the Indian Economy by Dr. S. Mahendra Dev
          Get by with a little help from friends (and shopkeepers): Household borrowing in response to

          Covid-19 by Dr. Ajay Shah and Dr. Renuka Sane
          Covid-19: The Invisible Vicious Foe by Dr. Namrata Gulati and Chandni Nanda





      I N T E R V I E W
          Dr. Srijit Mishra





      A R T I C L E S   F R O M   S T U D E N T S
          Shibanjan Dutta

          Sagar Kumar





      C A M P U S   A C T I V I T I E S
          Covid-19: Impact and Lessons Learnt by Jai Mohan Pandit, Registrar

          Library Services during Covid-19 by Library Team
          Campus Recruitment in a Pandemic-Struck Economy by Placement Committee

          Alumni Committee
          Kaawish





      F U N   C O R N E R
          Crossword

          Jumbled Words




      N O S T A L G I A]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[DIRECTOR                                                          DIRECTOR' S NOTE








                    IGIDR
















                                                       IGIDR, conceptualized as a think tank in

                                                       development policy by the then Reserve
                                                       Bank  of  India  (RBI)  governor  Dr.

                                                       Manmohan  Singh,  is  an  autonomous

                                                       research  body  founded  in  1987  by  the

                                                       RBI to commemorate its golden jubilee.

                                                       Its mission is to promote the study and
                                                       dissemination             of     knowledge,           and
      S. M AHEN D R A D EV
                                                       conduct         research         from        a     broad

       I am happy that IGIDR students                  interdisciplinary              perspective,             on

           are bringing out the first                  development             with        its      economic,
      quarterly issue of the newsletter.               technological,  social,  political,  and

       I thank the editorial committee
                                                       ecological  aspects,  to  gain  insights  into
       including faculty members and

       students for this initiative. This              the  process  of  development  and
       gives an opportunity for IGIDR                  alternative  policy  options,  with  special

        to showcase its academic and                   emphasis on social, legal, organizational
        non-academic activities of the                 and institutional aspects.

          institute. It can also create

           synergy between IGIDR
         activities and those of other
        academicians, policy makers,

          regulatory bodies, and the

      corporate sector. Thanks are also
       due to the IQAC sub-committee

        for their recommendations on
                the newsletter.
                                                                                                                  1]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Here,  I  would  like  to  share  the  message  given  at  the  directors  as  well  as  the  continuous  encouragement
    time  of  the  Silver  Jubilee  year  of  the  institute  in  and  support  of  the  Reserve  Bank  of  India  and  its
    2012/13  by  Dr.  Manmohan  Singh  who  was  the  then     successive Governing Board Members.
    Prime Minister. The message is the following.
                                                               The  research  agenda  of  IGIDR  is  guided  by
    “I  extend  my  greetings  to  the  faculty,  staff  and   contemporary  policy  concerns,  individual  faculty
    students    of   the   Indira   Gandhi    Institute   of   members’ research interests, and through sponsored
    Development  Research  (IGIDR),  as  the  institute        projects.  Theoretical  as  well  as  empirical  research
    celebrates its silver Jubilee this year.                   undertaken  over  the  years  covers  a  wide  range  of
                                                               topics and themes such as macroeconomics, banking
    It is with great fondness that I look back at the time     and  finance,  household  finance  and  financial  sector
    when  the  idea  of  IGIDR  was  conceived  during  my     regulation,   poverty,    inequality   and     human
    tenure as Governor, Reserve Bank of India. Though it       development,    food    security   and    agriculture,
    was initially conceived as an Economics think tank for     industrial  organisation  and  corporate  governance,
    the  country,  IGIDR  was  inaugurated  as  an  advanced   international  finance  and  trade,  development
    research institute in 1987 by the then Prime Minister      economics,  public  economics,  institutional  and  law
    Shri Rajiv Gandhi.                                         and  economics,  energy  and  environment  policy,
                                                               urban  economics  and  migration,  and  city  planning.
    I  am  happy  that  IGIDR  has  emerged  as  a  centre  of  These  areas  of  research  focus  reflect  the  diverse
    excellence  for  higher  learning  in  economics,  focusing  expertise  and  interests  of  its  faculty,  both  past  and
    on  academic  training  and  research  from  an            current.  IGIDR’s  research  would  continue  to  stay
    interdisciplinary and international perspective. It has    focused  on  various  developmental  problems  and
    gained status as a deemed university in 1995 and has       issues of policy relevance as they evolve from time to
    been  accredited  with  the  highest  ranking  for  its    time.  At  the  same  time,  the  Institute  recognizes  the
    teaching and research programmes.                          need  to  expand  its  research  profile  in  some  of  the
                                                               emerging  areas  to  maintain  its  stature  as  a  premier
    In these challenging times, our country needs quality      institution  for  research  in  economics  and  public
    academic inputs into the policy making exercise. It is     policy.
    this challenge that IGIDR should take up as it prepares
    for the years ahead.                                       The Institute will seek to enhance faculty strength –
                                                               both  regular  and  visiting  faculty  –  in  a  few  of  the
    I congratulate all those who have been associated with     emerging  research  areas.  A  decentralized  system  for
    IGIDR’s  growth  and  development.  I  wish  them  and     faculty and students has provided a free intellectual
    IGIDR all the best for the future."                        space  for  research  ideas,  within  the  broad  theme  of
                                                               Development.
    Over  the  years,  IGIDR  has  established  itself  as  a
    premier  research  cum-teaching  institute  and  its       Right  from  the  beginning  IGIDR  has  had  a
    current eminence derives in a large measure from the       tremendous impact on policy debates of national and
    efforts of its faculty, students and staff, successive     international importance. Going forward, IGIDR will






                                                                                                                  2]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[continue to stress on policy relevant research by its   Deemed  to  be  Univerisity  to  a  full-fledged  multi-
      faculty and students.                                   disciplinary university / higher education institution
                                                              (HEI).  This  requires  fundamental  decisions  to  be
      Right  from  the  beginning  IGIDR  has  had  a         taken  by  the  institute  on  all  aspects,  including
      tremendous impact on policy debates of national and     IGIDR’s mission and vision.
      international importance. Going forward, IGIDR will
      continue to stress on policy relevant research by its   It is important to have a broader and at the same time
      faculty  and  students.  The  Institute  will  continue  to  well  defined  area  where  the  institute  should  focus
      publish  the  widely  regarded  India  Development      while  planning  to  reorient  and  expand.  The  broad
      Report. The Institute will also encourage and provide   area of public policy is one such overarching theme,
      all possible support to its faculty for participation in  where  the  institute  can  leverage  on  its  current
      official  policy  making  Committees  of  various       strength. Apart from economics, a good public policy
      Ministries. Besides, the Institute will continue to play  HEI/university  should  have  multiple  departments
      a  leading  role  in  policy  debates  by  organising   such as, politics, international relations, demography,
      thematic  conferences  and  workshops  on  its  own     geography,    law,   management,      statistics,   and
      and/or  at  the  request  of  various  Government       environmental  studies  etc.  Thus,  expansion  along
      Ministries  /  policy  making  bodies.  Strengthening   these  lines  will  ensure  that  we  can  become  a
      teaching and expanding outreach activities are part     multidisciplinary HEI/university as envisaged in NEP
      of the vision.                                          but  with  great  synergy  among  the  various
                                                              departments.
      One of the immediate challenges of the institute is to
      align  with  the  guidelines  of  the  New  Education   In keeping with NEP-2020, the teaching programme
      Policy-2020    (NEP-2020)    announced      by    the   has to be diversified broadly on two lines: (a) The first
      government.                                             one  is  to  start  differentiated  degree  programmes  at
                                                              the  Masters  level  that  have  a  strong  core  in
      It lays down the government’s vision, approach and      Economics  but  specialisation  in  specific  application
      the framework for the entire education sector from      fields. Examples include M.Sc. in Financial Economics
      primary  education  to  higher  education.  The  NEP-   and M.Sc. in Energy and Environment Economics; (b)
      2020 has far reaching implications for IGIDR in terms   Second  one  is  to  start  a  4-year  B.Sc.  in  Economics
      of its nature, scope, size, and academic programmes.    programme.  In  this  regard,  the  Institute  could
      Fundamentally,  the  NEP-2020  would  require  IGIDR    consider some of the ideas described in the NEP-2020
      to transform from a single-discipline (albeit carrying  for 3-year and 4-year undergraduate programmes.
      out interdisciplinary research)






                                                                                                                  3]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[As a think-tank in public policy, IGIDR’s vision is to become the premier nodal
         centre for development research in India over the next 10 years for promoting
         cooperative  endeavours  with  other  Indian  and  International  scholars  and

         institutions; to organize courses, capacity building programs, conferences, and
         workshops  on  subjects  of  theoretical  or  practical  relevance  for  development
         and  policy  formulation;  to  publish  journals,  reports,  pamphlets,  books,
         research papers in furtherance of these objectives; and to provide consultancy
         to national and international institutions on issues linked to these objectives.
         The vision of IGIDR in the next decade is to further develop it as an Institute of

         high  international  standing  and  join  the  league  of  world  class  centres  of
         excellence  in  theoretically  informed  applied  research  and  teaching  in
         development  studies.  It  can  be  done  by  strengthening  the  present  areas  of
         research and diversifying its research and teaching to new areas to address the

         development challenges in tune with the changes in development paradigms,
         economy  and  society.  The  intellectual  ambience  of  openness  to  ideas  and
         plurality of perspectives have to be continued and strengthened.




                                                                       S. MAHENDRA DEV
                                                                                  Director






                                                                                                                  4]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[FACULTY ADVISORS' NOTE













                                                     Dear Readers,

                  ECONP₹ISM is a student-managed newsletter published quarterly by Indira Gandhi
                   Institute of Development Research, Mumbai. The newsletter is envisaged to create
                     awareness about essential work done at our Institute, to act as a platform that
                showcases academic and non-academic activities of the Institute, and to create synergy

                    between the Institute’s activities and those of other academicians, policymakers,
                                      regulatory bodies and the corporate sector.

                  The broad theme of the current issue is “Covid-19: Impact and Lessons Learnt”. The
                  current issue features regular articles and interviews of senior academicians, reports
                    on the Institute library's activities, reports on the Alumni committee’s activities,
                summaries of other student initiatives like ‘Kaawish’, and so on. Hence, we feel that this

                    issue contains a good mix of expert articles on the broad theme and the internal
                                               activities of the institute.

                 We would like to extend our heartfelt gratitude to the Director, the Dean of Students,
                  the Registrar, and the members of the Newsletter sub-committee for their guidance

                 and support. We would also like to take this opportunity to thank the contributors for
                 taking out their valuable time to provide articles for this issue. Lastly, we would like to
                  acknowledge the exemplary contributions of this issue’s student editors, who during
                these difficult times, worked with a lot of focus and dedication to get quality articles for
                                             this edition of the newsletter.

                 We hope that readers would enjoy going through this issue of the newsletter. We wish
                to engage and encourage more academicians, policymakers, and alumni of this institute

                                    to share their contributions to our future issues.

                                                      Best wishes,
                               Dr. Bharti Nandwani and Dr. Gopakumar Achuthankutty,
                                             Faculty Advisors, ECONP₹ISM









                                                                                                                  5]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[ARTICLES FROM



                                          EXPERTS




















                                                 ONE YEAR OF COVID-19 AND
      ONE YEAR OF
      COVID-19 AND THE                                  THE INDIAN ECONOMY

      INDIAN ECONOMY
                                                                  DR. S. MAHENDRA DEV
                                                 The evolution of cooking styles
           - by Dr. S. Mahendra Dev             One of the topics for this newsletter is the impact and lessons of
                                                Covid-19.  I  would  like  to  discuss  here  Covid-19  and  its  impact  on
                                                 Delivering newsletters through email is one of the best
                                                the  Indian  economy,  lessons  learnt  and  the  policies  needed  to
                                                 ways to build a strong relationship with your members and
                                                improve growth, jobs and equity. The coronavirus pandemic which
                                                 customers. Give them exclusive access to your latest
       GET BY WITH A                            is a once in a century event has affected both lives and livelihoods
                                                 collections, services, and limited offers while
       LITTLE HELP FROM                         in the last one year. The economic crisis that we are facing today is
                                                 simultaneously improving  the visibility of your brand. No
       FRIENDS (AND                             vastly different from any crisis that we have seen recently. This is
                                                 need to limit yourself to brochures or billboards. With a
       SHOPKEEPERS):                            the first economic crisis in recent memory that has been triggered
                                                 simple click, clients can be up-to-date on your newest and
                                                by a non-economic factor- ‘a pandemic'.
       HOUSEHOLD                                 biggest releases at home, work, and even while traveling.
       BORROWING IN                             What is the impact on Indian Economy?
                                                 Email newsletters can also help you grow your company.
       RESPONSE TOCOVID-                        The  pandemic  has  inflicted  two  shocks:  a  health  shock  and  an
                                                 After all, it only takes a few seconds for relevant
       19                                       economic shock. On health, India has 11.8 million corona cases with
                                                 information to reach your clients. That's why it's important
                                                1.61 lakh deaths by the end of March 2021. The overall fatality rate is
             - by Dr. Ajay Shah &                to have engaging content that will keep them subscribed
              Dr. Renuka Sane                   1.36  and  it  is  considered  one  of  the  lowest  across  the  countries.
                                                 for years to come. Add your logos, photos, and other brand
                                                Vaccination  drive  started  from  January,  2021.  Cumulatively  India
                                                 materials to make sure everything is clean and consistent.
                                                has  administered  around  6.5  crore  vaccine  doses  till  the  end  of
                                                March,  2021.  From  April  1,  vaccinations  also  started  for  the  age
       COVID-19: THE                            group  45-60.  The  second  wave  of  Covid-19  is  expected  given  the
       INVISIBLE VICIOUS                        recent spike in corona virus cases. Therefore, it is a biggest health

       FOE                                      shock for India since independence.


           - by Dr. Namrata Gulati              The  economic  shock  has  much  more  severe  for  India,  for  two
                &   Chandni Nanda               reasons. First, pre-COVID-19, the economy was already slowing

                                                                                                                  6]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[down, compounding existing problems of unemployment, low incomes, rural distress, malnutrition,
         and widespread inequality. Second, India’s large informal sector is particularly vulnerable. Out of the
         national total 465 million workers, around 91% (422 million) were informal workers in 2017-18.



         The  economic  shock  has  impacted  both  formal  and  informal  sectors.  The  growth  slowdown  of  the
         Indian  economy  during  the  pre  Covid-19  period  was  mostly  due  to  insufficient  growth  of  demand.
         During the pandemic time, both demand and supply were affected. On the demand side, consumption,
         investment  and  exports  have  been  subdued.  Domestic  and  global  supply  disruptions  have  led  to
         supply  side  problems  in  many  sectors.  There  have  been  massive  disruptions  in  global  production

         supply chains, tourism and trade.
         The problem of twin balance sheet has been accentuated further with more stress in corporate and
         financial  sectors.  The  MSME  sector  has  been  badly  hit  by  the  reduced  cash  flows.  In  the  banking
         sector,  NPAs  are  likely  to  increase  for  all  the  scheduled  commercial  banks,  NBFCs  (non-banking
         finance  companies)  and  micro  finance  institutions.  The  NPAs  could  be  much  more  for  retail  loans.
         There has been a disconnect between stock market and real sector performance. Agriculture is the
         only sector which showed a positive growth of 3% to 3.5% in 2020-21



         The lockdown has choked off almost all economic activity. But, the worst affected are the bottom of
         the pyramid particularly the informal workers including migrants. In urban areas, the pandemic has
         led to the widespread losses of jobs and incomes for informal workers and the poor. Estimates by the
         Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE) show that unemployment shot up from 8.4% in mid-
         March to 23% in the first week of April. There are about 40-50 million seasonal migrant workers in

         India. Media have broadcast images of hundreds of thousands of migrant workers from several states
         trudging  for  miles  and  miles  on  highways.  The  shutdown  has  caused  untold  misery  for  informal
         workers particularly the migrants who lead precarious lives facing hunger and malnutrition. Lacking
         regular salaries or incomes, these agriculture, migrant, and other informal workers were the hardest-
         hit during the lockdown period.


         The  second  advanced  estimates  show  that  India’s  real  GDP  would  decline  by  8%  in  2020-21  as

         compared to 2019-20. Some projections show the real GDP would increase by 10% to 11% in 2021-22. If
         we look at the levels, the real GDP in 2019-20 was Rs.145.7 trillion while it is expected to decline to
         Rs.134.1 trillion in 2020-21. Even if we have 10% growth, the level of GDP would be Rs. 147.5 trillion in
         2021-22 – this is only 1.1% higher than the level of 2019-20.
         According to CMIE, the employment rate is still 2.5 percentage points lower now as compared to the
         level  before  the  lockdown  last  year.  Women  lost  more  jobs  and  many  were  out  of  the  workforce.

         Inequalities increased in health care and education.


         What is the response of the government?
         The  Central  government  announced  a  comprehensive  economic  relief  package  called  the
         ‘Atmanirbhar  (self-sufficient)  package  which  had  three  components:  (i)  monetary  actions;  (b)  fiscal
         actions;  (c)  economic  reforms.  The  announcements  were  made  in  the  months  of  March,  May  and
         November in 2020. The Centre and the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) have together provided total fiscal

         stimulus of Rs. 29.87 lakh crore since the Covid-19 pandemic began. This amount is 15% of India’s GDP.
         RBI announced liquidity and measures worth of Rs. 12.71 lakh crore till the end of October, 2020.


                                                                                                                    7]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[The government package consists of measures for        reconstruction  company.  Fourth,  there  is  no
         the  poor  and  vulnerable  groups,  health,  MSMEs    additional tax in the budget. The expenditure will be

         (micro,    small   and     medium     enterprises),    borrowed  from  market  or  through  disinvestment.
         agriculture, manufacturing etc. It also includes the   Fifth, there is some push to health sector.
         much  debated  agriculture  reforms  which  became
         three  farm  laws  later.  On  manufacturing,  under   What are the lessons learnt and policies needed
         Atmanirbhar  3.0,  government  announced  Rs.  1.45    to improve growth, equity and employment?
         lakh  crores  production  linked  incentive  scheme    There are several lessons on different sectors due to

         for 10 champion sectors.                               the pandemic. First lesson is on health sector. Central
                                                                and state governments can tackle the current ‘second
         Apart from the Central government, several state       wave’  better  than  the  ‘first  wave’  of  corona  virus
         governments       have     initiated    innovative     because  of  the  experience.  We  need  to  improve
         programmes to help the informal workers and the        India’s  health  sector  at  different  levels  including
         unemployed poor. Kerala government for example         states  and  districts.  Second  lesson  is  on  lockdown.
         has announced a Rs. 20,000 crore package.              Initially, lockdown was needed to prepare for taking

                                                                care of the infected patients. It had adverse impact on
         There  are  some  good  things  in  the  recent  Union  livelihoods  although  it  might  have  saved  lives.  But,
         budget  2021-22.  First,  it  is  transparent  on  fiscal  overtime,  it  is  viewed  that  lockdown  is  not  the
         deficit numbers by including the earlier off-budget    solution  for  controlling  the  pandemic.  The  country
         numbers. Second, budget has given push to capital      has  to  live  with  the  pandemic  by  following  covid

         expenditure      and     infrastructure.    Capital    appropriate  behaviour  without  lockdowns  for  quite
         expenditure  increased  from  Rs.4.1  lakh  crore  in  some time.
         this  year  budget  to  Rs.5.5  lakh  crore  next  year
         budget  (around  35%  increase).  Further  Rs.  2  lakh  Third lesson is on education. Online education is not
         crore  of  capital  expenditure  were  allotted  for   efficient one as compared teaching physically in the
         states  and  autonomous  bodies  to  utilize.  Budget  classrooms.  There  is  also  digital  divide  in  education
         also  announced  a  DFI,  development  financial       between haves and have nots. Even those who have

         institution  to  promote  investment.  Third,  the     computers  and  other  equipment,  connectivity  is  a
         budget  made  directional  change  with  reforms:      serious problem in many areas of India. Fourth one is
         asset  monetization,  privatization  of  banks,  FDI   on work from home. It is not a problem for those who
         increase in insurance, setting up of asset             have relatively bigger houses to work from home. The

                                                                houses  are  too  small  to  work  from  home  for  the
                                                                middle class and the lower middle classes. The poor
                                                                and  informal  workers  including  gig  workers  can’t
                                                                afford to stay at home unlike the privileged organized
                                                                workers. Lastly, one big lesson is on migrant workers.
                                                                During  the  pandemic  time,  the  government  and  the

                                                                employers should take care of the migrants. There is
                                                                also need to protect the rights of migrants. We need
                                                                to put in place safety nets for them.
                                                                Turning to the economy, several policies are needed
                                                                to  improve  growth,  equity  including  jobs.    Some  of

                                                                the  economic  reforms  announced  may  help  in
                                                                reviving growth in the next few years by raising

                                                                                                                  8]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[investment,  reducing  the  twin  balance  sheet  problem  of  banks  with  NPAs  and  debt  problem  for  the
         corporate sector, increasing credit flow, solving supply side problems and improving exports. However,
         we discuss here on the policies needed for reducing inequalities as we are having ‘K’ shaped recovery.


         Covid-19 in the last one year has once again reminded us the growing inequalities in India. A recent Pew

         Research Report shows that India’s middle class may have shrunk by a third due to the pandemic while
         the number of poor people earning less than Rs.150 per day more than doubled. The Pew report also
         warned that the situation may actually be worse than estimated because of worsening inequalities.


         Inequalities were increasing earlier also but the pandemic has widened them further. For example, the
         share of wages declined as compared to that of profits. The big companies and large part of the corporate

         sector could manage the pandemic. The quarterly net profit of the BSE200 companies reached a record
         high of Rs.1.67 trillion in the third quarter of FY21 and was up by 57% year-on-year. But, the informal
         sector and workers have suffered a lot with loss of incomes and employment in the last one year. In
         other words, the recovery is more k-shaped with rising inequalities.


         Development  can’t  be  discussed  without  talking  about  inequality.  In  the  past  several  philosophers,
         economists and other social scientists have discussed about inequality. In recent years. Rising income

         and wealth inequality attracted the attention of IMF, World Bank, OECD and Davos meetings. With the
         release  of  the  book  by  French  economist  Thomas  Piketty  in  2014,  there  has  been  more  debate  on
         inequality  in  several  parts  of  the  world.  First  time  at  global  level,  a  goal  on  inequality  is  included  in
         sustainable  Development  Goals  (SDGs).  Goal  10  of  SDGs  is  about  reduction  in  inequality  within  and
         among  countries.  There  are  two  main  arguments  for  reduction  in  inequality.  One  is  ethical  or

         philosophical  argument  that  equity  is  important  for  its  own  sake  (intrinsic  value).  Second  one  is
         reduction in inequality is required for sustainability of growth (instrumental value). Therefore, there is a
         need for addressing inequality for sustainable growth and well-being.

         As  the  British  economist  Anthony  Atkinson  says
         “much is written about the 1 per cent and the 99 per

         cent.  But,  if  we  are  serious  about  reducing  income
         inequality,  what  can  be  done?  Reduction  in
         inequalities  is  important  for  its  own  sake  and  for
         improving  demand  which  can  raise  private
         investment,  consumption  and  exports  for  higher
         and sustainable economic growth.



         We concentrate here on three-pronged approach for
                                        SEE BLOG
         reducing  inequalities.  These  are:  (a)  focus  on
         employment  and  wages,  (b)  raising  human
         development  and  (c)  Quasi  universal  basic  income
         and other social safety nets.



         First, creation of quality or productive employment
         is central to the inclusive growth approach. At the
         macro level, investment ratewhich declined from

                                                                                                                  9]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[39% in 2011-12 to 31.7% in 2018-19 has to be improved. Investment in infrastructure including construction can
   create employment. In the recent budget, the central government has rightly focused on capital expenditure for
   infrastructure. There are eight challenges in employment: (a) creating productive jobs for 7 to 8 million per year;
   (b) correcting the mismatch between demand and supply of labour: Only 2.3% of India’s workforce has formal skill

   training  compared  to  96%  in  South  Korea,  80%  in  Japan,  and  52%  in  USA;(c)  Structural  change  challenge:
   Manufacturing should be the engine of growth. Here labour intensive exports are important. Manufacturing and
   services are complementary; (d) focusing on MSME and informal sector including rights of migrants; (e) Getting
   ready  for  automation  and  technology  revolution;  (f)  Social  security  and  decent  working  conditions  for  all;  (g)
   raising real wages of rural and urban workers and guaranteeing minimum wages.


   Second one is creating equality of opportunity by improving human development. Increasing public expenditure
   on health and education is another form of redistributive measure. Covid-19 has given us several lessons on health
   sector. Public expenditure on health is only 1.5 per cent of GDP. Apart from spending on vaccine and other related
   measures, we need to move towards universal health care and spend 2 to 3 per cent of GDP on health. Education
   and health achievements are essential for reducing inequality of opportunities. Great quality dichotomy exists in
   both  these  sectors.  There  are  islands  of  excellence  that  can  compete  internationally  in  education  while  vast

   majority of them churn masses of children with poor learning achievement. We also have the experience of digital
   gap in education during the pandemic. One has to fix this dichotomy in health and education.

   The third one is providing quasi universal basic income and other safety nets. For example, Dr. Rangarajan and
   myself suggested three proposals on minimum income for the poor and vulnerable in the post-pandemic period.
   These are: (a) cash transfers to all women above the age of 20 years; (b) expanding the number of days provided

   under  MGNREGA  (Mahatma  Gandhi  National  Rural  Employment  Guarantee  Act)  and  (c)  National  employment
   guarantee scheme for urban areas. In all these proposals, there is no problem of identification. A combination of
   cash transfers and an expanded guarantee scheme can provide income support to the needy.


   Apart from the above, increasing farmers’ income particularly small and marginal farmers is needed for reducing
   inequalities and creating demand. Farmer producer organisations should be strengthened. States have to be given
   more role in agri marketing reforms. Terms of trade for agriculture has to be improved.



   Enhancing tax and non-tax revenues of the government is needed to spend on the above priorities. The tax/GDP
   ratio has to be raised with a wider tax base. Richer sections have to pay more taxes. Similarly, the inequalities
   between Centre and states should be reduced in finances. State budgets must be strengthened to improve capital
   expenditures  on  physical  infrastructure  and  spending  on  health,  education  and  social  safety  nets.  Apart  from

   economic  factors,  non-economic  factors  like  deepening  democracy,  decentralization  can  help  in  reducing
   inequalities. Unequal distribution of development is rooted in inequalities of political, social and economic power.
   We have to find opportunities and spaces where the power can be challenged and redistributed. In the post-covid
   world,  addressing  inequality  is  important  for  higher  and  sustainable  economic  growth  and  well-being  of  the
   population.


                                                                                                                 10]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[GET BY WITH A LITTLE HELP FROM MY

          FRIENDS (AND SHOPKEEPERS): HOUSEHOLD

               BORROWING IN RESPONSE TO COVID 19




                                      AJAY SHAH & RENUKA SANE





        The lockdown in the early days of the Covid 19 pandemic in India impacted on on economic activity.
        Between  April  and  August  2020,  18.9  million  salaried  people  lost  their  jobs,  difficulties  were  faced  by
        migrant labourers, and small and medium businesses. Deshpande (2020) shows that overall employment
        dropped  sharply  post-lockdown,  with  larger  drops  for  women  than  men.  Household  incomes  were

        adversely affected. As an example, survey work by Lee, Sahai, Baylis and Greenstone (2020) shows that
        two  months  into  the  lockdown  poor  and  non-migrant  workers  in  Delhi  saw  a  drop  of  57%  in  their
        incomes,  with  9  out  of  10  workers  reporting  that  their  weekly  income  had  fallen  to  zero.  Bertrand,
        Krishnan and Schofield (2020) measure the fraction of households who say they are able to survive on
        their own for a week, and in April that value was 34% in the overall population and 50% or more for
        below-median household income.



        How  would  households  cope  with  such  a  shock?  Economic  theory  suggests  that  households  desire
        consumption smoothing. One mechanism for consumption smoothing is borrowing. For example, there
        was an increase in household borrowing after demonetisation (Karmarkar and Narayan, 2020; Wadhwa,
        2019; Chakraborty and Sane, 2019). This connects to the working of the financial system. While India has
        made  a  lot  of  progress  in  ownership  of  a  bank  account,  and  increased  electronic  payments,  access  to
        formal credit remains low.



        What do we expect about household borrowings?


        Borrowing during the Covid crisis is shaped by three factors:

        1. Income transfers: The government of India announced a stimulus package worth Rs.1.7 trillion after

        the lockdown. This included food security measures as well as direct cash transfers to poor households.
        This may have helped households deal with the immediate crisis.

        2. Low demand: As people were at home owing to the lockdown, demand may have been affected. It is
        also possible that households saw this job loss as permanent, and hence cut back on expenditures in a
        way they would not have had they seen this as a temporary disruption. This also fits with the view that
        precautionary savings increase after a deep crisis (Rajadhyaksha, 2020). However, this may be true for

        households  in  the  higher  income  distributions,  but  is  unlikely  to  be  the  case  for  those  below  median
        income.





                                                                                                                 11]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[3. Supply constraints: India's financial system has faced difficulties since 2012. This has manifested itself
         as  business  failure  at  ILFS  and  other  financial  firms,  large  and  small.  Credit  growth  was  decelerating
         prior to the lockdown. The difficulties for the financial sector increased when the Reserve Bank of India
         announced a moratorium on all loan repayments for three months from March to May 2020, and then
         extended it for another three months. These moratoriums made it more difficult for financial firms to

         assess the credit quality of borrowers. Overall bank credit growth was 5.8% in September 2020 compared
         to 8.1% in September 2019. From 2018 onwards, when certain borrowers faced supply constraints, they
         would  have  had  to  deleverage  (repaying  old  loans  while  not  getting  new  ones)  or  default.  The  grand
         question of the field consists of understanding the economic condition of households in India in 2020, in
         examining how consumption was held up through new kinds of labour supply and through borrowing,
         and in obtaining insights into these three distinct economic forces that are in play. In this article, we
         discover some new facts that contribute towards this overall research agenda.



         Methodology


         We source data from the Consumer Pyramids Household Survey (CPHS) for the months of May, June,
         July and August from the years 2016 - 2020. The borrowing data comes from the Aspirational India table

         within CPHS. Using this we ask three questions: 1. Did households have debt outstanding at the time of
         the survey? This helps us understand the total number of borrowers in the economy. 2. What are the
         sources from whom households have outstanding borrowings? This tells us whether households borrow
         from the formal or the informal sector. 3. What is the purpose for which households have outstanding


         borrowings?  This  tells  us  if  households  are
         borrowing for consumption expenditure, for
         consumer  durables,  or  for  running  their
         businesses.    CPHS    does    not    provide
         information    on    the   value    of   debt
         outstanding.  We  are,  therefore,  not  able  to

         analyse  the  impact  on  borrowing  on  an
         intensive  margin.  Our  analysis  is  restricted
         to   understanding     the   proportion     of
         households borrowing from various sources,
         for  various  reasons,  i.e.  on  the  extensive
         margin.  Household  weights  for  each  wave
                                                                            Table 1: Number and share of borrowers in the population
         are provided by CPHS -- these are used to get
         population estimates.

         Results: The number of borrowers Table 1 presents the number and percentage of households having
         debt  outstanding  in  the  months  of  May  -  August  in  each  of  the  five  years.  The  number  of  borrower
         households had been consistently increasing till 2019. In May - August 2016, 12% of the population had
         debt  outstanding.  This  increased  to  50%  by  2019.  The  number,  however,  fell  in  2020  to  45%  of  the

         population. The fall has been greater in urban regions than rural.






                                                                                                                 12]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Disentangling explanations: Sources of borrowing



          Given that a large proportion of households did not have enough to live on for more than a couple of

          weeks,  we  would  have  expected  a  huge  increase  in  the  number  of  borrower  households.  In  order  to
          investigate  the  sources  of  this  drop,  we  begin  by  analysing  the  role  of  the  financial  system  in  the
          household borrowing story by studying the sources of borrowing.


          Table 2 presents the percentage of borrower households borrowing from each source. We find that the

          biggest drop in borrowing is from banks: in 2019, 26% of borrower households had borrowed from banks
          - this has dropped to 20% in 2020. The proportion of households borrowing from money lenders has also
          dropped  -  from  7%  in  2019  to  4%  in  2020.  The  drop  in  households  borrowing  from  banks  and  money
          lenders was higher in urban regions than rural regions. There has been a lot of discussion in India about
          the increased risk aversion of banks. A fall in the number of borrower households may be a result of this
          phenomenon.





















                                                                   Table 2: Sources of borrowing



          There  has  been  a  concurrent  rise  in  the  number  of  households  who  have  borrowed  from  friends  and
          family from 14% in 2019 to 21% in rural regions, and from 13% to 27% in urban regions. The sharp increase
          in the borrowing from friends and family suggests that some smoothing of consumption expenditure is
          likely to have occurred using informal social networks that play an important role in the economic lives
          of those in developing countries (Munshi, 2014).



          Household borrowing from shops increased in rural India - from 52% to 58%, and fell slightly in urban
          India. It is interesting to recall that Chakraborty and Sane (2019) had found that between the years 2016
          and 2018 (i.e. after demonetisation), the biggest rise in borrowing was from shops, especially by those in
          the  lower  income  deciles.  This  seems  to  be  true  in  the  current  situation  as  well,  especially  in  rural
          regions.



          In  difficult  times,  it  was  not  banks,  money  lenders,  and  employers  that  mattered.  It  was  friends  and
          family, and the neighbourhood shops. It appears that non-financial firms and cash flow management by
          the retail supply chain have been more important than financial firms. The connections from the formal
          financial system to these shops could then be unusually influential.





                                                                                                                 13]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Disentangling explanations: Purpose of borrowing


         Examining the purpose for which households borrow can tell us something about the demand for credit.
         Table 3 presents the top five reasons for borrowing in 2020, and compares it with 2019.

         In May-August 2019, 62% of rural and 60% of urban borrower households had borrowed for reasons of
         consumption  expenditure.  In  May-August  2020,  this  had  risen  to  70%  and  66%  of  rural  and  urban
         borrower households respectively. This is consistent with the importance of consumption smoothing,
         and  of  many  households  not  having  enough  resources  to  survive  for  more  than  a  few  weeks.  The
         increase for reasons of consumption expenditure is higher in urban regions. Urban India was more likely
         to be affected because of both the Covid infections and the intensity of the lockdown than rural India.
         Income  transfers  from  the  government  are  also  likely  to  have  targeted  rural  households  than  urban
         households.




















                                                                Table 3: Purpose of borrowing

         There has been an increase in borrowing for business and debt-repayment reasons in this period as well.

         The numbers for rolling over debt went from about 9% to 12% of borrower households in urban regions,
         and from 7% to 9% of borrower households in rural regions. This suggests that households who would
         otherwise have serviced debt through business or personal income took recourse to borrowing when
         those cashflows subsided. A personal insolvency law that is able to provide some relief to debtors and
         allow for restructuring of the larger loans can help alleviate some of this stress.



         The  fall  in  the  number  of  borrower  households  seems  to  be  driven  by  the  fall  in  the  borrowings  for
         housing, durables purchase and investments. It is also likely that large purchases such as housing and
         durables are made through bank loans. The fall in the borrowings from banks may be a result of a fall in
         these large durable purchases.


         Conclusion



         We study the response of households on borrowings during the 2020 lockdown. We do not have data on
         the value of debt outstanding. We expected that there would be an increase in the number of households
         that borrow owing to the disruptions to economic activity. However, it is remarkable, that despite the
         large shock, overall, there has been a reduction in the number of households that borrow. This fall is






                                                                                                                 14]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[driven by fewer households borrowing from banks, and fewer households borrowing for housing, and
          consumer durables purchases. Households continue to borrow for consumption expenditure, business
          and debt repayment. The most utilised sources of borrowing are friends and family and shops.


          This work suggests many interesting possibilities for downstream research. For example, one can study
          the differences in borrowing patterns between households with different income and wealth profiles, as

          well as the correlation between sources and purpose of borrowing. It will also be possible to evaluate
          whether  income  transfers  from  the  government  led  to  a  fall  in  the  number  of  borrower  households.
          Similarly, one can ask whether different health outcomes play a role in their borrowing outcomes.


          The  number  of  households  choosing  to  borrow  has  been  different  from  what  happened  after
          demonetisation. There may be several reasons for this - the magnitude of the disruption, the length of
          time for which it lasted, the possibility of more permanent impacts on labour markets among others.

          This  leaves  us  with  interesting  research  possibilities  to  understand  household  behaviour  and  their
          interaction with financial markets.


          References


          Ashwini  Deshpande  (2020),  The  Covid-19  Pandemic  and  Lockdown:  First  Effects  on  Gender  Gaps  in

          Employment and Domestic Work in India, Working Paper 30, Ashoka University.
          Azim Premji University (2019), "State of Working India 2019", Technical Report, Centre for Sustainable
          Employment.
          Kaivan  Munshi  (2014),  "Community  Networks  and  the  Process  of  Development",  Journal  of  Economic
          Perspectives, 28(4), pp: 49-76.
          Kenneth  Lee,  Harshil  Sahai,  Patrick  Baylis,  and  Michael  Greenstone  (2020),  "Job  Loss  and  Behavioral
          Change: The Unprecedented Effects of the India Lockdown in Delhi", Working Paper, EPIC India.

          Marianne Bertrand, Kaushik Krishnan, and Heather Schofield (2020), "How are Indian households coping
          under the COVID-19 lockdown? 8 key findings", Rustandy Centre for Social Sector Innovation, Chicago
          Booth.
          Niranjan Rajadhyaksha (2020), "The covid shock could alter people's financial priorities", Livemint, 5 May
          2020.

          Sagar Wadhwa (2019), "Impact of demonetization on household consumption in India, Working paper.
          Subhamoy Chakraborty and Renuka Sane (2019), "Household debt over time", The Leap Blog, 24 May 2019.
          Sudipto  Karmarkar  and  Abhinav  Narayanan  (2020),  "Do  households  care  about  cash?  Exploring  the
          heterogeneous effects of India's demonetization", Journal of Asian Economics, 69.




          Sane  is  a  researcher  at  the  National  Institute  of  Public  Finance  and  Policy,  Shah  is  an  independent

          scholar. We thank four anonymous referees, Kaushik Krishnan, Radhika Pandey and Anjali Sharma for
          useful comments.


          (Republished from The Leap Blog)




                                                                                                                 15]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[COVID-19 THE


                                INVISIBLE VICIOUS FOE




                                NAMRATA GULATI & CHANDNI NANDA




        Covid-19 has affected our lives in a way never before. It has touched us in many unprecedented ways, far
        beyond what we could imagine. When it first invaded our territory, we were complacent and perhaps

        many of us refused to even acknowledge its arrival. We did not give to it the attention it was seeking.
        Slowly and steadily, it started spreading its tentacles and made everyone acknowledge that; we can’t
        trivialize its existence. Soon everyone was engulfed in fear that this invisible and potentially invincible
        enemy  might  embrace  us  anywhere,  and  we  may  not  even  get  to  know  about  it.  This  fear  was  there
        amongst everyone; rich or poor, male or female, child or adult. It assaulted everyone with equal dignity
        without  discriminating  on  the  basis  of  caste,  religion,  gender,  or  wealth.  This  virus  was  completely

        oblivious of the deep-rooted differences in human society which have prevailed for ages.


        But we were differently prepared to defend ourselves from this onslaught. We all started taking refuge
        in  our  shelters  to  guard  ourselves,  and  our  near  and  dear  ones.  Some  of  us,  called  upon  the  inner
        strength and courage to face the challenge. Some of us were more materially resourceful to withstand
        the attack and refused to be trampled by the unseen foe. Depending upon both our external and internal
        wealth and wisdom, we made a conscious decision not to wander in the unknown terrain where this

        enemy  was  more  dominating  –  like  the  overcrowded  place.  But  many  were  overpowered  by  the
        circumstances. They had no liberty to make choices –which could save them, keep their families secure
        or  make  them  stronger.  Apart  from  this  tangible  external  attack  on  health,  this  enemy  was  quietly
        seeking to change the way we conduct our lives. The entire economic machinery was up for a toss. The
        deep-rooted human relations were challenged.



        But, all of us were willing to take on the fight and were reluctant to give up so easily. Many of us had to
        make adjustments which we could never think of, but we were ready for this fierce battle not just for
        ourselves but also for the sake of those whom we held close in our hearts. We also felt the presence of an
        unseen  force  that  was  binding  us  together  and  making  us  more  empathetic.  We  took  this  as  an
        opportunity to serve others.


        Given our uniqueness, each one of us had a different tale to share about the sacrifices we made and the

        changes we accepted. A story that varied depending upon our internal strength, the courage we derived
        from our relations, from our resources, and from the agencies which were around to help us out.
        Who  are  the  people  who  emerged  undefeated?  What  were  the  factors  which  played  a  critical  role  in
        announcing  their  victory?  How  did  the  external  agency  help  those  who  were  not  strong  enough  to
        defend themselves? Was the help granted equitable or some people, based on caste, creed, and gender

        victim of some form of prejudice? How effective was this external support? Did this unseen




                                                                                                                 16]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[rival – without any intention, exasperate the existing difference which has prevailed in the society? Did
         it increase the differences between rich and poor and if yes, then how? Or did it provide opportunities to
         those who were underprivileged? Did females, who have been traditionally victimized -showed greater
         resilience during this pandemic? The answers to these questions are not so simple and straight. Many

         factors played a critical role. No matter how hard we try, we may not be able to do complete justice to all
         potential  theories.  But  even  if  we  are  not  able  to  thoroughly  apprehend  and  appreciate  the  role  of
         different  channels,  still  it’s  worthwhile  to  make  a  small  attempt  in  this  direction.  We  first  try  to  list
         down different dimensions in which our lives have been affected. None of the aspects is less important
         than the other, and each merits a detailed understanding.


         To complement our hypothesis and to better untangle the linkages, we used the data collected by Young

         Lives. The data has been collected for four countries: India, Ethiopia, Peru, and Vietnam. This data was
         collected using a phone survey rather usually conducted than face-to-face surveys due to the onset of
         this pandemic.


         The total sample used for India were 2000 children from the Younger Cohort (YC), i.e., those who were
         born in 2001-02, and the rest 1000 children from the Older Cohort (YC) who born in 1994-95 from Andhra

         Pradesh and Telangana. In the first phone call (between June 2020 to July 2020), a total of 2,750 young
         people (1,863 of Younger Cohort respondents aged 18, and 887 Older Cohort respondents aged 25 years
         old)  were  questioned.  The  idea  of  this  survey  was  to  gauge  the  individual’s  understanding  of  the
         pandemic.


         In the second call (between August 2020 to October 2020), a total of 2,754 young people (1,868 Younger
         Cohort respondents aged 18, and 886 Older Cohort respondents aged 25) were questioned. This time the

         focus was primarily to look at the impact of Covid-19 on the labour market, education, and health of
         people.

         Now,  we  come  back  to  pertinent  questions  that  this  pandemic  has  raised.  Who  were  the  people  who
         were most affected by the virus in terms of their mental health? Was this enemy able to play on the

         individual's vulnerabilities and pose a more emotional threat to one set of people relative to the others?
         Did the adversaries that women faced right from their birth make them better prepared to take up the
         challenge? Or were they subjected to more torment because of the increased burden of the household
         chores and taking care of children?


         From  the  data,  we  have  created  an  anxiety  score  which  can  take  a  value  from  0  to  9,  a  higher  value
         reflecting a higher value of anxiety. From the graph labelled "Mean Anxiety by Gender", it is evident that

         the mean level of anxiety was higher for females relative to males. The possible reason for it, as validated
         by  the  data,  was  the  increased  burden  of  household  chores  and  taking  care  of  children.  A  larger
         proportion of females concurred that there was an increase in the time spent in taking care of child care.
         Similarly, around 60 per cent of females agreed that the burden of the household chores increased. It's
         pertinent  to  note  that  an  already  huge  percentage  of  women  are  overwhelmed  by  household
         responsibilities and are operating at the threshold level. Any addition to that load would greatly exhaust

         them.


                                                                                                                 17]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[18]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Next,  we  seek  to  compare  the  stress  level  amongst  people  belonging  to  different  age  groups.  Were
        children  left  more  perturbed  due  to  the  restriction  on  their  freedom  or  were  they  more  relaxed  than
        before  as  had  more  time  to  bond  with  their  parents,  grandparents,  and  siblings?  Were  old  left  more
        anxious because of the looming threat of falling sick easily and taking longer to recover?


        Depending on the age, we had divided people into 4 groups. ‘Young child’ were those who were below 15

        years old. Between 15 and 30 were categorized as ‘Young’; 30 – 55 as ‘middle-aged’ and anyone above 55
        were categorized as ‘old’. From the data, we find that the stress level was highest amongst young child
        and old relative to the other categories.





























        The income level of the household is also a very important determinant of their level of stress. Were poor
        now made more conscious of their deprivation as many had to continue to go out to seek work to sustain
        their  families?  They,  unlike  their  rich  counterpart,  did  not  have  the  luxury  to  switch  to  the  online
        platform. The following graph laid credence to the theories proposed and we find that the mean anxiety
        increased with the material deprivation of the household.




                                                                                                                 19]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Next, the critical issue that we would like to focus on is the gap between rich and poor. Here again, there

        are many dimensions, and all are vital components in explaining the change in gap. First, let’s talk about
        students. All students, especially the younger ones, were given online instructions. But the poor were
        constrained because of the lack of resources to receive lessons. Whereas people who were on the other
        end of the income spectrum could arrange for the tailor-made private tuitions at home, and this was
        over and above the formal training that they were receiving from their educational institution.


        It is evident from the graph labeled; "Reason for not attending the class by Household Type", that it was

        the  poor  who  were  scared  badly.  Many  of  them  had  to  give  up  on  education  because  of  the  lack  of
        resources.


        The  pandemic  gave  a  choice  to  work  from  home  to  those  who  were  resourceful  and  skilled,  but  the
        others who were already less privileged people were left without work. At times, for the sake of meeting
        basic needs for their families they were forced to take up jobs which increased the threat of their getting

        infected by the virus and transmitting it to their families.


        However, not just poor but even the well-off people experienced the loss of job. Maybe, many businesses
        were left unviable and had to be shut because of lack of demand. In fact, according to the data, people
        who thought that they were highly well-off reported a higher percentage of job loss compared to the
        others.


                                                                                                                 20]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[21]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[The other subtle effect that the pandemic had was on the prices of commodities and goods and services.
          Because of the lack of supply, certain essential items became scarce leading to an increase in prices. This
          increase in price for the same good varied from one location to the other. The places which had a higher
          concentration of the rich experienced higher increase in the prices – because of the higher willingness to
          pay  of  those  who  were  better-off,  making  the  more  vulnerable  ones  worse-off.  The  following  graph

          highlights the differences in the different regions:













































          We  see  that  more  than  50  per  cent  of  the  people  residing  in  the  urban  region  said  that  they  had

          experienced an increase in prices. Making a similar comparison between people belonging to different
          income  categories,  we  find,  that  the  people  who  identified  themselves  as  belonging  to  the  struggling
          category reported the highest increase in prices. Even rich people reported an increase in the prices. The
          only income category where the higher percentage reported no increase in prices was those who were
          very rich.



          Covid-19  also  completely  altered  how  the  labour  market  functions  –  it  made  some  sectors  and  some
          economic activities gain whereas there were many sectors whose existence was completely nullified. No
          amount of intervention was good enough to mitigate the mighty impact of the pandemic.


          As time will pass, other significant ways in which individuals and the economy has been affected will
          become evident. And, there will be many more ways in which the virus will continue to affect our lives

          which  will  get  revealed  only  with  time.  But  yes,  we  do  all  concede  that  it  was  one  demon  that  had
          potential much greater than we could realize



                                                                                                                 22]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[We  see  that  more  than  50  per  cent  of  the  people  residing  in  the  urban  region  said  that  they  had

         experienced an increase in prices. Making a similar comparison between people belonging to different
         income  categories,  we  find,  that  the  people  who  identified  themselves  as  belonging  to  the  struggling
         category reported the highest increase in prices. Even rich people reported an increase in the prices. The
         only income category where the higher percentage reported no increase in prices was those who were
         very rich.


         Covid-19  also  completely  altered  how  the  labour  market  functions  –  it  made  some  sectors  and  some

         economic activities gain whereas there were many sectors whose existence was completely nullified. No
         amount of intervention was good enough to mitigate the mighty impact of the pandemic.


         As time will pass, other significant ways in which individuals and the economy has been affected will
         become evident. And, there will be many more ways in which the virus will continue to affect our lives

         which  will  get  revealed  only  with  time.  But  yes,  we  do  all  concede  that  it  was  one  demon  that  had
         potential much greater than we could realize






































        Acknowledgement:


        The  data  used  in  this  publication  come  from  Young  Lives,  a  15-year  study  of  the  changing  nature  of
        childhood  poverty  in  Ethiopia,  India  (Andhra  Pradesh  and  Telangana),  Peru  and  Vietnam
        (www.younglives.org.uk). Young Lives is core-funded by UK aid from the Department for International
        Development (DFID). The views expressed here are those of the author(s). They are not necessarily those
        of Young Lives, the University of Oxford, DFID or other funders.



        Namrata Gulati is a professor at South Asian University. Chandni Nanda has recently received a Master's
        degree in Economics from Shiv Nadar University and has helped in compiling the graphs.



                                                                                                                 23]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[In




                                                              Conversation





                                                             with Dr. Srijit




                                                                       Mishra





                                                       Q1. For us, the last year has been a year full
                                                       of  transitions  and  adaptations  –  to  new
     P R O F E S S O R   A T   I G I D R               technology,  to  a  new  world  and  to  a  new
                                                       life,  as  a  whole.  What  has  been  your
                                                       experience  of  life  in  the  past  one  year?  I
          He has served as Director                    mean  what  are  the  realizations  and

         at NCDS, Bhubaneswar and                      challenges  that  the  pandemic  has  revealed
           also worked as the ICCR                     to you?
           Chair Professor of Indian

           Studies at NCCU, Taiwan.                    It  was  both  good  and  bad.  Thankfully  I  didn't  have  to
              He has also been an                      travel  and  relocate  when  the  pandemic  was  at  its  peak.
         International Guest Scholar                   About adapting to the situation, currently, I am teaching
                                                       Contemporary issues in Human Development and Policy
          at Meiji University, Japan                   through a virtual medium. I had my own inhibitions about
           and a Subir Chowdhury                       how  the  course  would  move  ahead,  as  my  approach  is
            Fellow on Quality and                      generally  interactive.  I  like  to  ask  questions  and  get

          Economics at LSE, London.                    feedback.  My  teaching  progress  is  dependent  on  the
         He has also been a member                     responses I get.    Now,  as  I  am  completing  this  course,  I
           of numerous committees                      sense  that  it  has  gone  reasonably  well.  Challenges  like

             under Government of                       power-cuts, network issues, etc. have of course been part
           India. His research area                    of it. But, we need to get used to such uncertainties. If one
               includes Applied                        can  find  answers  to  the  question  on  how  to  deal  with

           Development Economics                       uncertainty, it would be rewarding as one can then move
               (Agriculture/Rural                      on to the next phase of life with an ability to handle such
                                                       situations.
            Development, Human                         Q2.  Do  you  think  that  online  teaching  is  a
                 Development,                          solution  in  the  pandemic  given  the
                Measurement of                         infrastructure  India  has?  What  are  your
           Development Indicators,                     thoughts on this and what measures do you

          Public Health and related                    suggest to make the transition better?
           issues), Public Policy and

                 Game Theory.
                                                                                                                 24]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[I  think  institutes  with  lesser  student           difficult  in  a  pandemic  situation.  Some
             strength  or/and  those  with  better                 online  forms  and  telephonic  surveys
             infrastructure  can  address  technological           (including video formats) have come up,
             issues  better.  For  example,  if  students          but  they  cannot  substitute  for  physical
             faced  difficulties  at  IGIDR,  one  could           presence.  Besides,  the  question  of
             provide a laptop, send materials by email             sampling  design  in  the  absence  of
             or upload recorded classes.                           population listing raises other questions.
             When  one  thinks  of  rural  areas,  the             I will take a digression and discuss some
             challenges  increase.  They  may  either              of my fieldwork conducted in the past.
             have  no  access  to  network  connections;
             or  may  be  in  a  family  that  has  a  single      Back  in  2005-06,  at  IGIDR,  we  carried
             phone  for  all  family  members.  The                out  this  study  on  farmers’  suicide  in
             solution  to  this  has  to  be  situation            Maharashtra.  Statistically,  suicide  is  a
             specific.  I  recall  having  read  how  a            rare  event.  Our  list  of  incidences
             teacher  in  a  remote  village  put  down            superimposed to a map indicated that on
             lessons in the walls facing the streets so            an  average  there  was  only  one  instance
             that  students  can  read  them  when  they           of death by suicide in a 30-40 kilometre
             pass  by.  In  another  instance,  the  school        radius. Hence, one cannot design a study
             used its public announcement system to                of  selecting  a  few  villages,  listing  the
             impart  lessons.  In  such  times,  decision          population  of  these  villages  and  then
             making  at  the  local  level  helps  improve         drawing  a  sample.  Our  sample  design
             access to learning.                                   covered  more  than  110  villages.  In  each
             NCERT started an initiative of recording              village,  we  surveyed  the  household
             lectures  and  telecasting  them  through             where  death  by  suicide  occurred,
             their  designated  television  channels.              selected  a  control  household,  discussed
             There  have  been  civil  society  initiatives        with  knowledgeable  people  and  held  a
             to bridge the digital divide by providing             focus  group  discussion  to  have  an
             mobile  phones/tablets  to  students  to              understanding  of  the  socioeconomic
             access  learning  materials.  A  mix  and             scenario. The team also had to be trained
             match  approach  with  technology  and                to handle matters sensitively. The reason
             local-level  initiatives  to  ensure  that            I  am  bringing  this  here  is  to  point  out
             everyone  has  access  to  resources  for             that  the  situation  made  us  innovate
             learning should be the way forward.                   survey  tools  and  designs.  It  is  another
                                                                   matter  that  the  report  led  to  important
             Q3. How do you think the work                         policy decisions by the state and central
                                                                   governments.
             of  data  collection  has  changed
             due  to  the  pandemic?  What  is                     In  spite  of  its  policy  impact,  a  friendly
             the        way        forward         for             academic  critic  once  asked,  “Did  the
             researchers in this regard?                           farmers  benefit  finally?”  This  led  me  to
                                                                   civil  society  organizations  who  work
                                                                   with  farmers  to  develop  research
             Some of you would be pursuing a career                protocols  that  document  evidences.  In
             in research. In certain domains of applied            2015, when I joined NCDS, we submitted
             development research, fieldwork is very               a  proposal  of  collaborative  action
             important. One should understand what                 research to the Government of Odisha to
             is happening at the the ground level. But,            revive cultivation of millets, a nutritious
             this will be                                          and climate resilient crop, in






                                                                                                                 25]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[tribal areas. The programme started in 2017 and included four verticals: increase production
             through new agronomic practices, facilitate processing units, develop marketing channels, and
             revive  consumption  including  their  inclusion  under  supplementary  nutrition  programmes.
             This  being  an  action  research,  an  essential  requirement  is  obtaining  regular  feedback  from
             different  stakeholders  –  farmers,  consumers,  civil  society  functionaries,  and  staff  of  line
             department of government among others. In the initial days of the pandemic, with the first
             phase  of  lockdown,  all  this  completely  stopped.  More  importantly,  colleagues,  across  the
             board,  got  involved  in  COVID-19  related  work.  Subsequently,  some  attempts  were  made
             through telephonic interviews and online meetings to get some feedback. This paved the way
             to articulate a case to consider workers involved in agricultural activities are also like workers
             involved in public utilities. This was helpful for agriculture in general, but also for the millets
             initiative.  By  the  time  I  left  NCDS  in  early  September  of  2020,  more  than  one  lakh  farmers
             were associated in the programme through the production vertical.

             In economics, we have been trained to incorporate learnings from statistics and mathematics,
             but when it comes to fieldwork we also take lessons from anthropology. Or, as they say, “Go
             and soil your dresses.” That means, go and be part of the people that you are trying to study.
             That is always helpful.

             In fact, in the human development course, a component of fieldwork exists and I am happy to
             state that some of the students in the current batches who have opted for this course provide
             us  some  important  lessons  of  conducting  fieldwork  during  this  ongoing  pandemic.  Some  of
             them conducted face to face interviews, if situation permitted, but in most cases it was done
             virtually. They have a rich repository of cases of the people they see around (such as vendors,
             teachers, comparing public sector versus private sector professionals, people who lost jobs or
             had a cut in salary, and women who have to balance between their on-line work and increased
             domestic responsibility) and how has the pandemic affected their lives.

             The  pandemic  also  strengthened  collaboration  of  researchers  with  network  of  civil  society
             members  or  teachers  of  schools/colleges  in  local  areas  to  document  the  return  of  migrant
             workers across the country, which has led to a number of publications by scholars from across
             the country. There is an increasing use of social media to not only elicit responses on one’s
             questionnaire, but also to use that medium as one’s field location, that is, to be a participant
             observer  of  a  forum  that  one  is  a  member  of.  There  are  scholars  who  did  some  fieldwork
             between the two spikes and are following up subsequently through a virtual mode.

             What one foresees is that fieldwork is increasingly going to be a combination of physical-cum-
             virtual mediums, more use of technology even when one is conducting physical fieldwork, and
             a greater possibility of collaboration with local facilitators including perhaps school children
             who  may  get  a  first-hand  exposure  to  research.  Besides,  documenting  the  change  in  the
             method and medium of fieldwork could also be an important area of study.

             I paraphrase Jean Drèze who, as you all know, is one of the foremost development economists
             in India. He had once remarked that one day’s fieldwork is equivalent to six months of library
             work. The field is indeed a very intriguing space and in fact, lot of theoretical and analytical
             observations can come from the field. I would suggest that those of you who are interested in
             doing research, even when you are working in the corporate world as a researcher, be familiar
             with your field - whatever that field may be.








                                                                                                                 26]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Q4.  We  have  seen  that  this                       One  can  bring  in  other  aspects  of
             pandemic  has  brought  out  in                       inequality  like  caste,  class,  gender,  and
             the  open  a  lot  of  inherent                       regional differences among others. Each
                                                                   of  them  is  equally  relevant  and
             developmental             inequalities                important and we need to address them.
             between  the  poor  and  the                          These    kinds     of   challenges    are
             ultra-rich.  It  has  deepened                        continuous: today, you may address one

             inequality        in      terms        of             kind of problem, and, tomorrow, another
             education,        healthcare        and               kind  of  problem  might  emerge.  We
                                                                   should  be  sensitive  to  such  new
             other  basic  necessities.  What                      dimensions  of  inequality  and  explore
             are  your  thoughts  about  this                      possibilities of addressing them.
             and  how  can  we  fight  this

             inequality  as  a  nation  or  even                   I recall Mahatma Gandhi’s talisman, one
                                                                   of his most powerful social philosophies
             as a global citizen?                                  that  he  shared  with  us  a  couple  of

             I think these are important challenges for            months  before  his  death.  He  said  that
             us. These inequalities can be in multiple             whenever  in  doubt,  think  of  the  most
             domains.  First,  we  should  understand              vulnerable person that you have in mind
             how and where they are. Then, we have                 and  then  you  think  about  the  decision
             to  engage  at  multiple  levels.  One  thing         that  you  are  going  to  take.  If  this
             which I have been thinking about in the               decision will be of some help to this most
             last  couple  of  weeks  is  that  this               vulnerable  person,  then  all  your  doubts
             engagement with the market needs to be                will melt away. Ambedkar, who also had
             substantial  for  the  people  who  are  left         the vulnerable in his thinking, gave us a
             out. Let me elaborate on what I mean by               very  civilized  way  of  addressing  such
             that. For instance, if there is a player with         concerns  through  debates,  discussions,
             a  substantial  market  share  then  this             and  evidence-based  reasoning  that  the
             player  will  be  at  an  advantageous                parliamentary  form  of  democracy  gives
             position  both  as  a  buyer  and  as  a  seller.     us.  One  doesn't  have  to  be  violent  to
             But,  at  the  same  time,  smaller  entities         articulate  one’s  case.  I  think  these  are
             cannot  have  that  bargaining  leverage.  It         important  lessons  that  both  of  them
             is for this that those who work with the              have  given  us  and  we  can  use  them  to
             vulnerable  at  the  grassroots  to  address          address these inequalities.
             inequality,  also  need  to  work  towards
             strengthening  the  market  share  of  the
             vulnerable.                                           Q5.  We  know  that  the  one  of
                                                                   the biggest tragedies of 2020 in
             Besides, a      large  number  of  buyers  and        India,  apart  from  the  health
             sellers,  as  some  argue,  can  lead  to  fair
             prices  because  no  one  player  is                  crisis caused by Covid has been
             influencing  them.  Now,  if  one  player  is         the sufferings that the migrant
             able  to  influence  prices  then  that  could        labourers  had  gone  through.
             lead  to  substantial  inequality.  A  case  in       And they are an integral part of
             point, without getting into the scientific            our     metropolitan         economy.
              merit behind the evolving and complex
             science, is the pricing of vaccination and            And this migrant labor crisis is
             related concerns.                                     still a visible reality in 2021 ......






                                                                                                                 27]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[....  which  proves  that  we  haven't  done  anything  substantial  to  help
             them  out  and  provide  them  stable  employment.  So,  what  are  your
             thoughts  on  this  and  how  do  you  think  India  can  address  this  issue?
             Also, what does this overall reveal about Indian society and economy?


             Indian society obviously has lot of layers - class, caste, regional and various other disparities.
             And, as I said earlier, we should be more sensitive to these inequalities and more so during the
             ongoing pandemic. Getting back, at the global level, one comes across the Great Barrington
             Declaration and the John Snow Memorandum. These are two broad schools of thought among
             medical scientists to address the pandemic.

             The  Declaration  takes  a  position  that  everyone  is  not  equally  vulnerable.  There  are
             demographic differences observed across age and gender and other factors. And hence, with
             reasonable restrictions the relatively less vulnerable people should be allowed to work while
             those with greater vulnerability (particularly, those with co-morbidities that have greater risk
             factors) are to be kept at a safe distance. This approach is sensitive to migrant labourers and
             their plight. In particular, the approach would suggest that they stay in their destination and
             not return back to their native places.
             As  against  this,  the  Memorandum  has  been  in  favour  of  stricter  restrictions  until  a  safe

             therapeutic  or  medical  intervention  is  available.  While  not  being  explicit  about  livelihood
             concerns, their stricter restrictions would also pre-empt any uncalled for mobility. As an aside,
             currently, vaccination is being rushed through. Even if one allays the scientific concerns on
             account of emergency approval (that is, without going through some checks and balances that
             is  done  under  normal  circumstances),  there  can  be  other  major  challenges  regarding  its

             availability, access, supply chain logistics, public health infrastructure, and the reduced focus
             on other medical conditions. This position has larger economic costs.
             On  mobility,  I  would  also  like  to  refer  to  Nicholas  Christakis  who  is  a  physician  turned
             network sociologist. He wrote a book Apollo’s Arrow where he studied pandemics from 1917-18
             onwards  and  provides  insights  for  the  current  pandemic.  He  and  his  colleagues  have  also
             recently  tracked  the  mobile  phones  that  passed  through  Wuhan  in  January  2020,  before
             lockdown was enforced there, and observed that there is a positive association between the

             distribution  of  these  mobile  phones  across  China  with  the  distribution  of  incidences  of
             infection  from  Covid  in  these  regions.  In  short,  mobility  amplified  through  network  has  an
             important role in the spread of the infection. Given this, restriction on mobility will be helpful.
             But,  this  requires  other  enabling  provisions  so  that  people  are  provided  with  food,  shelter,
             health care, and are also compensated for their livelihood.

             Q6.  You  talked  about  the  decentralised  approach.  Who  do  you  think
             would  take  the  responsibility  in  rural  area  or  even  in  a  municipality?
             What  would  be  the  policy  suggestion  according  to  you  for  this
             decentralised approach?

            A benefit of doubt could have been given in 2020 but if someone says that they have still not

            developed these things in 2021, one would be surprised. Odisha, which has some strengths in
            disaster management were the first state to declare lockdown in March 2020 when there were
            fewer cases. Further, Government of Odisha, much before the first peak,


                                                                                                                 28]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[during  the  return  of  native  migrants,            Q7.  Some  macroeconomists  in
             provide broad guidelines and authorised               India  are  of  the  view  that
             the sarpanch with the power of a district             spending  on  NREGA  should  be
             magistrate  along  with  some  amount  of
             financial autonomy.                                   increased as it is considered to
                                                                   be  a  business  cycle  stabiliser.
             Today,  in  2021,  after  one  year  of               What  is  your  view  on  NREGA
             experience  we  should  have  been  much              spending  during  the  Covid
             more  prepared.  This  is  so  because  the           period?
             past  pandemics  have  shown  multiple
             spikes.  Even  if  one  were  to  believe  that       Yes,  of  course,  if  people  are  not  able  to
             the current virus in on its wane, there is            get  enough  jobs  at  the  local  level  then
             talk among experts that one could expect              NREGA can be of help. Extension of the
             similar  kind  of  virus  in  the  future.            scheme to urban areas (as suggested by
             Whether it takes the form of a pandemic               Drèze  on  account  of  job  losses  in  the
             or  not  is  a  different  point,  but  localised     pandemic)  will  also  be  welcome.  The
             impact  are  likely  to  be  there.  All  these,      scheme being demand-based has in-built
             call  for  strengthening  the  local  bodies,         checks  and  will  not  be  a  burden  on
             not  just  to  address  an  emergency                 exchequer  if  alternative  opportunities
             situation, but with permanent features to             are  available.  However,  note  that
             improve availability and access of public             provisioning  for  NREGA  in  the  budget
             utilities,  and  to  strengthen  the  local           estimates  for  2021-22  when  compared
             economy.  This  will  also  allow  decision-          with the revised estimates of 2020-21 has
             making at the local level with evidence-              decreased  by  -35%.  With  reduction  in
             based  reasoning,  which  means  that                 funds,  those  implementing  the  scheme
             research  capacities  that  feed  into  public        will dissuade job creation under NREGA.
             policy  also  need  to  be  strengthened  at          The pandemic is a time when additional
             the local level.
                                                                   budget  could  have  been  allocated  for
                                                                   such schemes.
             On  evidence-based  reasoning,  one  is
             reminded  of  an  opinion  attributed  to             The  activities  under  NREGA  could  be
             John  Maynard  Keynes  who  when                      linked  to  boost  the  local  economy.  For
             confronted that he seems to be changing               instance,  allowing  work  in  one’s  one
             his  position  had  pointed  out  that  if            farms.  Maharashtra  had  done  this  in  its
             evidence  changes  then  he  changes  his             EGS, prior to NREGA. In Palghar, earlier
             position.  We  should  be  pragmatic  and             part      of      undivided       Thane,
             allow  people  to  take  decisions,  and  not         implementation of EGS led to revival of
             admonish them for mistakes when their                 rural economy through agricultural and
             intentions  were  honest  and  sincere,  but          horticultural   development.    It   also
             they  should  be  open  to  gathering  of             brought  about  reduction  in  seasonal
             evidence    and   evaluating   these   to             migration,   increased   enrolment     in
             examine  and  revise  their  position  when           schools,  and  increased  consumption  of
             required. It is important that people who             fruits that are nutritionally beneficial. At
             take  advantage  of  this  for  their  rent-          the  same  time,  if  not  implemented
             seeking  activities  are  kept  away  from            properly,  these  could  lead  to  rent
             such positions.
                                                                   seeking.  In  other  words,  NREGA  can  be
                                                                   positively  used  with  necessary  checks
                                                                   and  balances.  If  used  appropriately,  it
                                                                   can have multiplier effects.




                                                                                                                 29]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[ARTICLES FROM




                                       STUDENTS








































       A TALE OF TWO IN                         A TALE OF TWO IN THE CITY
       THE CITY
                                                                  SHIBANJAN DUTTA
         -By Shibanjan Dutta


                                                How about someone stuck in a house which isn’t even just a set
                                                of four walls with a roof over it, let alone the attributes which
                                                make  it  a  home?  How  about  waking  up  every  day  to  a  reality
                                                with  horripilation  and  threat  of  existence,  same  as  what  had
                                                haunted  you  in  your  dreams  a  few  hours  ago?  Sounds

       AN                                       sensationalised  right?  Yes,  it  would  have  seemed  the  same  to
       ETHNOGRAPHIC                             me,  a  snippet  out  of  a  Hollywood  fiction,  if  the  COVID-19
                                                lockdown didn’t turn this into a reality. While most of us were
       STUDY OF THE                             commenting on the news and plight of the thousands with some
       EFFECTS OF                               mere  words  on  social  media,  we  were  implicitly  shedding  off

       PANDEMIC ON                              responsibilities  with  false  hopes  on  institutions  taking  care  of

       DAILY WAGE-                              them.  This  article  is  based  on  a  set  of  telephonic  surveys  that
       EARNERS                                  were  conducted  on  the  urban  poor  and  I  hope  to  revisit  a
                                                glimpse of the reality that haunted many during the COVID-19

            - By Sagar Kumar                    lockdown.

                                                                                                                 30]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Rina Singh had earlier been an ayah at a private hospital. She didn’t have the luxury of the
              sophistication of being termed as a nurse. Later in time she wasn’t accepted for re-joining

              after  going  through  the  trauma  of  a  tumour  surgery  which  made  her  memory  somewhat
              impaired.  Her  husband  had  abandoned  her  long  back  leaving  behind  two  daughters  and  a
              son. Both of her daughters had been married off in spite of one being just 20. Her only son
              hardly  cared  for  her,  with  him  having  shifted  away  to  a  different  place.  Rina,  55  normally
              earns her living by taking care of patients, after being privately hired by families on a daily
              basis.  Now  as  lockdown  was  imposed  on  the  city  and  public  transport  made  unavailable,
              neither  was  she  demanded  by  her  employers  nor  was  she  able  to  visit  their  places  which
              happened to be some 10 kilometres away from her home. Being a daily wage worker, no one

              was obligated to pay her. Near about one month into the lockdown she had to cycle 20 odd
              Kilometres to her earlier places of work in hope of some assistance only to return with 400
              rupees. Her savings dipped nil and with little hope of normalcy, time could any moment have
              become  a  measure  of  hunger  for  her.  Adding  to  the  problems  were  the  statuses  of  her
              daughters. The husband of one had been fleeing for over one month now in the fear of being

              quarantined, since he migrated back to the city after the lockdown had been imposed. The
              other  daughter  Priyanka  compulsively  added  to  Rina’s  financial  burden.  I  happened  to
              survey Rina and one of her daughters and the state of affairs that unfolded was nothing but
              disturbing.

              When Rina Singh approached the so called authorities for free ration, she was plainly denied
              on the pretext that her son was associated with a political party which differed from theirs.
              Rina in frustration came back home only to throw away the flags and emblems of the party

              which  belonged  to  her  son  in  a  nearby  field.  “Do  I  look  like  a  beggar  at  their  mercy?”
              exclaimed Rina at despair. Both of us knew that situations would force her to give up her cry
              on social justice and eventually frame herself as a beggar adding one more justification to the
              tags  bestowed  upon  us  by  the  developed  nations.  From  the  land  which  advocated  social
              justice  in  its  capability  approach,  this  is  nothing  but  a  very  tragic  irony.  Her  daughter
              illuminated another side of the story. Priyanka was a part of a joint family in one of the slums
              some 4 kilometres away from her mother’s house. She had recently been on conflicting terms

              with her in-laws which made matters more severe for her during the period.


              Her husband was thrown out of his job and he gave into his habit of alcohol a bit more. It was
              a well known secret for them now that alcohol could be bought at a higher price from the
              very personnel’s who had been in charge of prohibiting the sales during lockdown. To make
              matters worse she even got denied of the local distribution facilities which happened to exist

              in  her  locality  with  the  people  there  citing  the  fact  that  others  in  her  family  had  already
              opted for it. Unfortunately none was shared by her family with her. Her one year old child’s
              medical  expenses  and  minimal  ration  needs  were  thus  taken  care  of,  by  her  already
              distressed mother Rina.










                                                                                                                 31]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[The narratives of Rina and Priyanka challenged          challenged  the  food  distribution  schemes.
         every bit of the social and economic fabric. No         Furthermore  most  people  were  unaware  of
         one  with  a  brain  tumour  would  cycle  20           other  government  schemes  that  existed  thus
         Kilometres  for  some  money.  The  distribution        revealing  the  need  for  awareness  programs

         systems  were  ought  to  be  instruments  for          among them. But it’s worth mentioning that the
         assistance and not mercy. The whole institution         provision for free ration, despite being faulty in
         of joint family collapsed in the case of Priyanka.      implementation had helped a lot of people.
         The  pandemic  which  withdrew  the  basic  self-
         reliance  opportunities  from  people  had  no          After  witnessing  such  sequence  of  events,
         silver  lining  for  people  like  them.  In  the  city  asking  them  about  their  update  on  social
         where  the  two  are  mere  representatives,  the       distancing  seemed  like  a  question  from  a

         duality of population as a whole had never been         distant future. When a whole slum relies on two
         such worse.                                             public  taps  for  drinking  and  non-drinking
                                                                 needs,    when     community       toilets   are
         Most  of  the  housemaids  I  interviewed  had          overburdened,  how  can  they  ensure  social
         emerged to be the sole bread earners for their          distancing even if they wished? Sometimes the

         family  thus  altering  the  ‘stereotypical  pre-       issue of job loss seemed to have hit them so had
         historic’  gender  roles.  Most  of  their  sons  and   that  the  answers  of  every  question  turned  out
         husbands had been thrown out of employment              to be a request for a job. While some expected
         now.    Sushoma     Achariya,    a   housemaid,         financial  assistance  after  the  survey,  some
         mentioned in despair how her son who earlier            repented  about  their  unawareness  after
         used to be a transporter is now trying his luck         learning just the names of so many government
         on  selling  vegetables  only  to  watch  most  of      schemes that existed.
         them perish. The influx of many such vegetable

         sellers  had  managed  to  keep  the  prices  at        With a second wave of the pandemic at the brim
         competitive  levels  but  businesses  such  as          and  speculations  of  a  second  lockdown  rising,
         grocery  shops,  medicine  shops  had  started          we  can’t  afford  to  forget  the  misery  that  was
         charging a premium. This higher price of living,        inflicted on a major proportion of people. While
         along with steeply falling incomes had taken a          many  obligations  towards  them  could  be

         toll  on  their  real  income  more  than  ever.  To    dodged  by  a  simple  notion  of  ‘Act  of  God’  and
         mitigate  this  when  they  turned  their  faces        suddenness  of  things  in  the  first  time,  if  there
         towards  the  local  ration  shops,  excuses  start     happens  to  be  a  second  lockdown,  and  such
         emerging.  Digitised  ration  cards  had  suddenly      experiences re-emerge, we would be held much
         gained utmost importance and people without             more  responsible  for  being  unable  to  cushion
         them      were     plainly    denied     rations.       off their miseries yet again!
         Unavailability  of  goods  at  the  fair  price  shops

         was also an issue. The situation emerged to be
         such that half of the ration from the shops were
         procured  by  the  local  party  offices  to  rebrand
         them  under  a  political  colour  and  some  were
         being procured by local businesses at a slightly        Shibanjan  Dutta  is  a  M.Sc.  student  of  2019-21
         higher price. The existence of such leakages            batch.





                                                                                                                 32]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[AN ETHNOGRAPHIC STUDY OF THE

              EFFECTS OF PANDEMIC ON DAILY WAGE-

                                                  EARNERS


                                                  SAGAR KUMAR
































      In this article, I will try to analyze the radical transformation in the daily lives of common people of our
      country due to the coronavirus pandemic with the help of the experiences of people working in the informal
      sector like hawkers, vegetable vendors, pakoda-sellers, etc. by using ethnographic research methods. Also, I
      will try to explain how these people have themselves evaluated this change and have been surviving despite
      it.

                                                                                   OTHER NEWS
      In the first quarter of the twenty-first century, all the socio-economic aspects of common life were going
                                                                                   AND
      through  severe  turns  of  ups  and  downs.  In  the  first  decade  of  the  new  millennium,  we  saw  how  the
                                                                                   DEVELOPMENTS:
      economies of nations like India and China reached high growth rates and started contributing to the world
      economy majorly. However, the first decade ended with one of the most significant crises of modern times -
                                                                                   T o u r i s m   G e t s   a   B o o s t
      the 2008 Financial Crisis – which originated in the U.S. but impacted most of the leading economies. Now,
                                                                                   i n   J u l y   -   3
      unfortunately, the second decade of the millennium is coming to an end with a pandemic that has already
      affected us badly enough to completely change the course of our daily lives. I hope by the end of the first
      quarter of this century, we overcome this disease and regain a sense of normalcy in our lives.


      As we all know, in the first quarter of the 20th century, the Spanish flu led to many deaths and changed
      social life radically. Along with the flu, came calamities like famines and many other diseases which spread
      very rapidly and altered the daily life of people across the globe as well as across India. A similar event is

      taking place in the 21st century as well when people are suffering from the coronavirus pandemic across the
      world, and they are having to adapt to radical changes in their daily life. Almost everybody on the planet is
      affected by this pandemic directly or indirectly. No matter who they are, what are they doing – some way or
      the other, their daily lives were changed to an unimaginable extent.



                                                                                                                 33]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[This analysis is based on the study I conducted in    Initially, they thought that the lockdown will be
           my  residential  area  where  around  10-12  street   only for a day but the day after Sunday, when
           vendors gather daily and sell different items like    P.M.  announced  that  the  lockdown  will
           pakoda, samosa, pani-puri, dosa, pan, vegetables,     continue for a week and then further extended
           etc.,  and  thereby,  earn  a  respectable  income.  I  it for 21 days, they were at a loss about how to
           personally  know  almost  everyone  because  most     maintain  their  daily  lifestyle.  As  they  have  no
           of them sell their items just behind my shop and      other source of income and are fully dependent
           many  of  them  buy  their  raw  materials  from  my  on what they sell on a daily basis, the thought
           shop.  So,  it’s  convenient  for  me  to  interact  with  itself  of  surviving  a  complete  lockdown  was
           them for the purpose of this ethnographic study       very difficult for them to fathom.
           as I have watched them selling these items from
           my  early  childhood.  The  only  change  that  I  had
           noticed  in  all  this  while  is  the  hierarchical  At the onset of the lockdown, they didn’t quite
           transition in ownership which has been gradually      understand its basic motive and were overall a
           taking place from generation to generation.
                                                                 bit  critical  of  the  government’s  moves.  In  the
                                                                 early days of the lockdown, listening to various
           When  I  started  to  talk  to  them  regarding  this
           study, initially they seemed to feel very awkward     rumors doing the rounds, they thought that the
           and  hesitant  as  nobody  like  me  had  approached  virus  only  infected  people  who  came  from
           and  tried  to  initiate  such  a  conversation  with  China  and  other  foreign  countries.  However,
           them before. At first, they outright asked me why     after  a  few  days,  when  they  started  to  get  the
           I  am  doing  this  and  don’t  I  have  to  study  big  actual  idea  about  the  virus,  how  it  spreads
           bulky  books  since  I  am  currently  enrolled  in  a  rapidly  and  affects  our  health  system,  they
           higher degree course. They wanted to know then        eventually  started  appreciating  the  actions  of
           where  lies  the  significance  of  this  study  in  the  the  government.  Moreover,  during  the  first
           context  of  the  curriculum  of  my  course.         phase  of  the  lockdown,  they  were  allowed  to
           According to them, students should only study to      sell their food items till 7 p.m. according to the
           get  “jobs”,  otherwise  join  the  family  business  or  state government guidelines since at that time
           parental  profession.  They  don’t  have  any  idea   the cases in Jharkhand were quite low. But later
           about   this   kind    of   analysis   which    is    on,  when  cases  started  to  rise  in  our  district
           understandable given nobody in their family has       (Dhanbad),    then    our   District   Collector
           even  completed  the  higher  secondary.  n  their    announced complete lockdown, and only ration
           families,  usually,  people  study  till  class  6-7  and  shops  and  vegetable  shops  were  allowed  to
           very few of them go for matriculation in the local    open along with the . . .
           government school. So, I started the conversation
           by  trying  to  explain  what  this  is  all  about  –  the
           topic  and  purpose  of  my  analysis  and  thereby,
           earn some confidence from them after which, in
           3-4  days,  the  conversation  between  us  became
           quite fluid. Since I knew them very well, I didn’t
           have to face any kind of difficulty in getting from
           them the specific information I required for this
           study.    First  of  all,  like  us,  they  were  all  very
           shocked  and  in  panic  when  they  came  to  know
           about  the  complete  lockdown  after  listening  to
           the Prime minister’s speech on 23rd March, 2020














                                                                                                                 34]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[medical clinics and shops, although just for the      procure  the  vegetables  for  selling.  They  had  to
         limited  period  of  6  hours.  This  selective       leave  their  homes  daily  around  4  a.m.  as  the
         allowance  for  shops  to  function  actually  made   market stayed open only from 4-6 a.m. They also
         these small vendors, in a sense, a bit jealous and    had to face the problem of credit then as, before
         they  started  complaining  about  the  guidelines    the  lockdown,  sellers  in  the mandi  gave  them  a
         of  the  government.  Meanwhile,  many  of  them      time  window  to  sell  their  products  and  pay  the
         started  making  a  shift  towards  other  kinds  of  price  within  10  days.  They  couldn’t  avail  this
         professions  like  selling  coal,  etc.  When  the    mechanism  of  deferred  payments  now  and  had
         shops  were  finally  announced  to  open,  the       there are a few policies that are still quite helpful
         prices  of  every  necessary  good  and  those  of    to  them  for  their  survival  but  the  point  to  note
                                                               here is that they, in no way, should be construed
         staple foods started to rise steeply due to high      as any favor to them by the government. Lastly, it
         demand  and  it  became  very  difficult  for  the    has been easily noticeable to me that, like most of
         local  shops  to  completely  meet  this  high        us, they are also very optimistic people and live
         demand. Many of them were selling their items         with the hope that the vaccine will arrive as early
         from their home itself, but the sale was half or      as possible and reach everyone across the society
         less  than  half  of  what  they  used  to  sell  in  the  as they have seen with other vaccines like Polio
         normal times. When others came to know about          vaccine in the past. In this article, I have tried to
         this  selling-from-  home  option,  they  also        give  a  comprehensive  overview  of  how  the
         started to think differently and went on to sell      pandemic  has  radically  transformed  the  lives  of
         their products by going to different localities on    the  common  people  around  us  who  work  in  the
         cycles  or  motorcycles.  Many  of  the  sellers      informal  sector  and  are  worst  hurt  by  the
         started  to  use  sanitizer  very  frequently  and    pandemic.  This  article  still  leaves  out  certain
         wore  gloves  although  they  had  never  heard  of   issues which were personal to the people studied
         sanitizer  before.  Some  of  them  even  started     and  hence,  they  didn’t  want  to  discuss  with  me
         accepting online payments through Google Pay,         but are still important in addressing the concerns
         PhonePe,  etc.  So,  one  positive  thing  that  came  the  pandemic  has  raised  about  the  situation  of
         out of this lockdown was their getting to know        the daily wage-earners of our nation. I hope any
         about  how  to  use  these  payment  methods          policy that is framed in the future to mitigate the
         which  helped  make  their  business  digital  to     adverse  effects  of  the  pandemic  takes  into
                                                               account  the  struggle  of  these  people  and  hence,
         some  extent.  However,  selling  on  bikes  and      provides  the  economy  with  a  more  balanced
         cycles  increased  their  input  costs  by  quite  an  version of development.
         amount,  and  hence,  their  profit  margin
         decreased.  Since,  they  already  earn  a  very
         moderate  amount  of  income  (about  ₹200-           Sagar Kumar is a M.Sc. student of M.Sc. 2020-22
         250/day, on an average), this further lowered it      batch.
         to ₹150 or less owing to lesser sales and higher
         input costs.

         The case with vegetable hawkers was different
         because before the lockdown they had to travel
         around  5  km  to  get  the  vegetables  from  the
         mandi,  but  as  the  mandi  is  a  highly  crowded
         space, the police had to strictly stop all activity
         over there. So, now they had to travel far away
         from the local wholesale market - around 25 km
         per day to










                                                                                                                 35]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[COVID-19: IMPACT AND


                              LESSONS LEARNT






                                              JAI MOHAN PANDIT




































       The  COVID-19  started  in  India  in  the  beginning  of  2020.  The  subsequent  lockdown  announced  by  the
       Government of India on March 24 impacted the education sector like any other sector for which no one,
       more  so  the  education  sector,  was  unprepared.  The  entire  organisational  functioning  of  the  Higher
       Education  Institutions  (HEIs),  such  as;  student  admission,teaching/research,conducting  examinations,
       academic  administration,  campus  maintenance,  student  learning  support  systems  including  the  library
       and IT facilities, campus safety, and security measures, were re-engineered with a paradigm shift.



       IGIDR was prompt to take immediate action and decided to send the student’s home. For several HEIs, it
       was  the  Holi  /  spring  break,  and  few  students  were  already  on  vacation.  The  promptness  and  the  HEIs
       proactive actions saved several lives and resulted in overcoming a lot of hassles. IGIDR allowed some of the
       students to stay back, realising their practical problems. We ensured necessary hostel stay arrangements,
       including the food, safety, and hygiene issues. By the time lockdown was announced, the majority of the

       students had returned home safely.


       Despite  the  numerous  challenges,  most  HEIs,  particularly  the  national  HEIs  located  in  the  metros  and
       cities, quickly geared up to meet the pedagogy challenges, experimented with novel methods, and achieved
       adorable  success  in  the  process.  IGIDR  had  dealt  with  it  by  being  very  agile,  and  agility  was  vital  even
       before the government announced the lockdown.Some of the HEIs initially had to face many challenges,
       which resulted in delays and even cancellations of several academic programs, including exams/admission

       tests, etc.



                                                                                                                 36]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[The other important issue was about being able           IGIDR  being  a  residential  campus,  had  an
        to   function    normally.   There    were    two        additional  responsibility  to  take  care  of  the
        dimensions:     i)   the   Institution's   smooth        campus  community.  Institute  appointed  a
        functioning  and  ii)  continued  teaching  &            COVID-19 task action force committee chaired by

        research  work.  It  is  highly  laudable  that  both    our  Director.  The  committee  had  a  very  tough
        academic and non-academic employees played a             task to ensure the safety, security protocols etc.,
        crucial  role  in  ensuring  the  smooth  functioning    of  he  campus  community.  The  UGC  and  other
        of the Institute. We already had some digital and        regulatory bodies too played a very proactive role
        online systems in place. However, the COVID-19           in providing the relevant guidelines to the HEIs
        has pushed us to use these systems proactively.          from time to time.



        The  moment  students  reached  home,  the  focus        The  management  of  the  IGIDR,  faculty,  non-
        shifted from planning to explore online teaching         academic staff, and other support teams, played a
        and giving remote access to the library resources        very  pro-active  role  in  ensuring  the  smooth
        and other study materials. Few HEIs had to face          functioning of the Institute. Every employee got
        challenges  for  enabling  online  education.            involved in the mission of smooth functioning of
        Challenges also involved encouraging employees           the   Institute.   All   these   events   involved

        and  students  to  get  conversant  with  the  online    meticulous  planning,  swift  action  from  the  top
        systems such as computer systems at home, the            management/authorities,      hard    work     and
        software required to get connectivity, etc.              dedication  from  both  the  academic  and  non-
                                                                 academic sides. Our staff members, including the
        We  started  deliberations  on  dealing  with  those     Administration,    Accounts,    Estate,   Library,
        students  not  having  access  to  the  internet         Students  Office,  and  particularly  the  IT  team
        facility  in  some  remote  places.  IGIDR  tried  to    members,  had  to  work  very  hard  to  ensure

        support such students with additional facilities.        seamless  support.  In  normal  conditions,  the
        Accordingly,  the  concerns  of  the  students  were     employees of the HEIs are expected to work for
        addressed  in  the  best  possible  way  in  a  short    eight hours a day. However, there were no such
        time.  We  provided  needy  students  with               limits  during  the  pandemic  crisis,  and  the
        laptops/digital  gadgets  on  a  loan  basis.  We        employees  had  to  stretch  beyond  regular  duty
        supported our faculty members to upgrade their           hours, including the weekends and the holidays.

        teaching aids. We also temporarily provided our
        staff  with  laptops/desktops,  enabling  them  to
        work  from  home  and  even  reimbursing  their
        cost towards internet connectivity.




        We initiated various academic events and large conferences during 2020-21. In normal circumstances
        organising  an  event  involves  a  lot  of  effort.  Even  though  it  has  several  benefits,  the  physical
        organisation  of  an  event  has  particular  challenges  of  ensuring  adequate  attendance  and  substantial
        financial commitments, etc. However, during the COVID-19 time, we could organise academic events
             "There's nothing quite like feasting on delicious food and drinking
        very efficiently in the online mode. The online way also improved the quality of attendance drastically.
                               good wine with your family and friends."
        People participated not only from India but from different parts of the world too. Likewise, several HEIs
        organised  the  academic  programs  online  during  the  pandemic  times.  The  attendance  of  the  quality
        people also gave a significant boost to the brand building of the HEIs.



                                                                                                                 37]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[As  we  advance,  most  likely,  the  hybrid  model  would  stay  for  some  more  time  in
           higher education institutions. One can do things online, so certain things probably
           will  continue  in  physical  space.  However,  online  programs  can't  ever  replace
           physical campuses. Students learn from teachers, learn from their batchmates and
           seniors  through  actual  interaction.  They  also  learn  from  students  from  other
           subjects by being present in the library, cafeteria, etc. So, while virtual teaching may

           extend the reach of only one source of learning, it compromises on the advantages of
           physical  campus.  Other  extracurricular  activities  are  equally  important  for  the
           overall development of students; they are also getting compromised. We should look
           at an interim arrangement to mitigate the damage caused by COVID-19 rather than
           as an ideal system.



           On  the  other  hand,  risks  are  involved  for  those  HEIs  who  won't  go  with  the
           flow.COVID-19  has  taught  us  the  importance  of  digital/online  systems,  flexible
           governance  and  automation.  To  maintain  quality  and  efficiency,  a  significant
           investment is required to facilitate the digitisation systems in the HEIs.










                                                                     Jai Mohan Pandit is the Registrar at IGIDR.




                                                                                                                 38]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[LIBRARY




       SERVICES DURING




       COVID-19






                                             LIBRARY TEAM





    Since  the  pandemic  struck  in  March  2020,  IGIDR

    Library  is  making  all  the  efforts  to  meet  the
    information  needs  of  faculty  members,  students,
    and  staff  albeit  remotely  and  to  some  extent
    physically  to  the  on-campus  users.  The  overall
    experience  was  different  even  though,  we  had
    some digital services from pre-Covid times.



    Immediately,  after  the  physical  library  was
    closed,  we  started  off  with  our  email  support
    services,  sending  the  required  papers  and  data
    requests  from  the  subscribed  e-resources  and
    links  for  free  e-books  made  available  by
    publishers.  Soon,  we  realized  this  may  not  be

    adequate  to  meet  the  users'  demands  24x7.
    Hence,  we  embarked  on  providing  off-campus
    access  to  subscribed  e-resources.  With  the  kind
    help  of  INFLIBNET  and  the  IT  team  of  IGIDR,  we
    were able to setup ‘Shibboleth’ off-campus access
    to subscribed e-journals and e-databases.





    This move augmented and helped in better access and utilization of e-resources by the faculty members
    and  students.  In  addition,  the  institute’s  VPN  access  was  also  made  available  to  access  some  of  the  e-
    resources, which were not accessible through ‘Shibboleth’. Moreover, we are regularly answering users’
    queries received through emails and issuing printed books to on campus faculty members and students

    and, also to others staying in Mumbai as and when requested.


                                                                                                                 39]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[During  the  pandemic  and  the  period  of  lockdown,    on  migrating  library  servers  to  new  ones  to
         the  second  big  challenge  was  upkeeping  of  the      make these systems robust for future use. We
         physical library and its resources from dust, insects,    were  able  to  do  all  this  with  the  support  of
         and humidity. We took off this journey and with the       authorities  library  committee  members  and

         help  of  Estate  department  could  get  the  library    staff of all the departments and support teams.
         cleaned  and  pest  controlled  on  a  periodic  basis
                                                                   In the post-Covid era, we perceive, libraries are
         initially and from August 2020 on a regular basis, so
                                                                   going  to  be  resilient  and  regain  their
         that the library can be put for immediate use as soon
                                                                   momentum. However, as it happened after the
         the  institute  reopens.  During  these  challenging
                                                                   emergence of the Internet, there will be some
         times with the limited on campus staff support, we
                                                                   amount  of  shift  in  users’  behavior  regarding
         continued  to  acquire  new  resources,  conducted
                                                                   the  use  of  the  physical  library  and  its
         library  committee  meetings  and  events,  renewed
                                                                   resources,  but  they  will  continue  to  use  print
         subscriptions  to  both  print  and  online  journals,
                                                                   resources  for  reasons  of  non-availability  in  e-
         handling  of  day-today  administration,  contributing
                                                                   formats and secondly, the libraries will not be
         metadata  of  IGIDR  working  papers  to  RePEc,
                                                                   able  to  procure  the  e-versions  owing  to
         bringing  out  monthly  ‘ÉconBuzz’  newsletter  on  a
                                                                   enormous  cost,  which  is  usually  ten  times
         regular basis and sharing useful information through
                                                                   higher than the printed books. In addition, the
         email and library Twitter handle ‘@igidrlib’. Among
                                                                   licensing  issues  and  subscription  mode  of
         the new resources, procurement of course specific e-
                                                                   procurement  will  also  prevent  this  from
         books,  was  challenging  as  many  of  these  were  not
                                                                   happening especially in the case of e-books.
         available  in  e-formats,  however,  we  put  in  our
         efforts in procuring the available ones and provided

         access remotely. Now, we have also begun

























     We  believe,  in  the  future,  IGIDR  library  users  would
     adore the physical library, as much as they like to read
     resources from their personal devices and comforts of
     their  homes/hostel  rooms.  We  will  thrive  hard  and
     change ourselves to changing times as change is always

     constant,  which  will  help  us  see  the  things  as  seen  by
     our  users.  Also,  try  our  best  to  save  our  users  from
     ‘infodemic’.




                                                                                                                 40]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[CAMPUS RECRUITMENT

     IN A PANDEMIC


     STRUCK ECONOMY





                              PLACEMENT COMMITTEE












        The legacy built by the alumni and faculty at IGIDR, along with the determination of students facilitated
        a  successful  campus  recruitment  season  amidst  an  economic  slowdown  that  preceded  the  pandemic
        during the summer of 2020, as the institute's administration worked hard to build digital infrastructure

        and  an  academic  calendar  that  would  ensure  students’  academics  continued  unhampered,  the
        placement  committee  at  IGIDR  faced  a  different  challenge  of  coordinating  with  companies  that  had
        offered  summer  internships.  The  revised  academic  calendar  had  overlapped  with  the  summer
        internship duration and it seemed impossible to manage both. However, with the help of concessions
        from  companies  and  the  grit  showed  by  students,  the  summer  internship  program  was  a  success  in

        terms of the record number of corporate internships and pre-placement offers. But the situation was
        about  to  get  much  more  challenging  for  the  placement  committee  when  it  became  clear  that  the
        pandemic was here to stay and would have a severe impact on the final recruitment that was supposed
        to be held later that year.
                                                                    The challenge being faced by the committee
                                                                    was  two-fold.  The  first  was  that  the
                                                                    economic  slowdown  caused  many  firms  to
                                                                    cut back on recruitment numbers and some
                                                                    even froze hiring. This was going to have a
                                                                    direct  effect  on  the  institute’s  placement

                                                                    statistics.  The  other  challenge  was  that  the
                                                                    pandemic  had  made  the  existing  on-day
                                                                    placement  process  obsolete.  It  had  to  be
                                                                    replaced  by  a  completely  new  process  that
                                                                    was to be built from scratch and had never

                                                                    been  tried  before.  The  rolling  placement
                                                                    process, which is generally followed by most
                                                                    other  institutes,  is  not  feasible  for  IGIDR
                                                                    due to the small batch size and the strictly
                                                                    enforced rule against rejection and multiple
                                                                    offers.




                                                                                                                 41]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Challenges of a New Normal                             faculty  advisors  and  members  of  the  administration

                                                             was also important to establish clear communication
                                                             between  the  various  stakeholders  so  that  all  the
                                                             processes could be conducted smoothly.


                                                             The Way Forward




                                                             The  rapid  growth  in  the  field  of  data  analytics  and
                                                             artificial intelligence has created many opportunities
                                                             for   students   to   have   a   robust    conceptual

                                                             understanding of statistics and econometrics. This is
                                                             also  evident  from  the  fact  that  many  prestigious
                                                             institutes  across  the  country  are  now  offering
      Therefore,  IGIDR  has  been  following  a  placement
                                                             dedicated courses and degrees in Data Analytics. The
      week  system  that  is  much  more  fast-paced  and
                                                             students  of  IGIDR,  an  institute  known  for  its
      gets  completed  within  a  day  or  two.  It  was
                                                             specialization in econometrics courses, stand to gain
      important  to  preserve  the  essence  of  the
                                                             a lot from this digital revolution.
      placement  week  process  so  as  to  benefit  from  it
                                                             While IGIDR enjoys a good reputation among various
      while  keeping  in  mind  the  limitations  of  the
                                                             industry  leaders  and  recruiters,  there  is  much  that
      virtual setup.
      The  employment  market  across  the  country          needs to be done to realize our full potential. One of
                                                             the biggest advantages of having a small batch size is
      witnessed  a  sharp  widening  of  inequality  during
                                                             that  every  individual  with  an  idea  can  make
      the  pandemic.  While  on  one  end,  thousands  of
                                                             themselves heard and ensure their ideas are put into
      people  were  losing  jobs  and  unemployment
                                                             action.
      reached  record  high  levels,  on  the  other  end  the
                                                             A  good  placement  record  has  a  positive  spillover  on
      most prestigious and well-known institutes across
                                                             attracting talented students from across the country.
      the  country  saw  an  improvement  in    their
                                                             This  will  not  only  ensure  a  more  diverse  set  of
      placement statistics. In order to be situated at the
                                                             students  but  also  help  us  achieve  our  vision  of
      fortunate  end,  the  students  needed  to  be  well
                                                             developing  as  an  institute  of  high  international
      equipped  with  the  knowledge  of  their  course
                                                             standing and join the league of world-class centers of
      material  along  with  other  skills  that  are
                                                             excellence.
      considered  desirable  in  the  industry.  To  facilitate
      sharing  of  such  knowledge,  the  placement
      committee came up with multiple new initiatives
      such  as  the  internship  discussion  program,
      sessions  with  immediate  seniors,  etc.  Having
      regular meetings with the entire batch as well as


                                                                                                                 42]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[ALUMNI DISCOURSES IN A


                                           PANDEMIC





                                           ALUM NI CO M M ITTEE
























      IGIDR  Alumni  Association’s  Alumni  Discourses  is  one  of  the  best  initiatives  started  by  our  super-senior
      batch. We hope it'll continue to increase our span of knowledge, thanks to the overwhelming participation of
      our alumni.
      I can proudly quote, "If you have a garden and a library and the support of your alumni, then regardless of an

      academic  or  a  corporate  career,  you  have  everything  needed  to  succeed!"  Our  alumni  have  distinguished
      themselves in various fields and established their careers in different parts of the world.
      This year, we successfully conducted three episodes of Alumni Discourses with an aim to connect with people
      from different backgrounds. In the first episode, we had Ms. Sohini Choudhuri (Assistant Vice President at
      Credit Suisse) and Ms. Ritu Ghosh (Associate Director at UBS) from the M.Sc. 2016 batch, who are working
      extensively in the corporate sector. The two guests gave us an idea of how the corporate world works, the
      kind of challenges that one may face, and how to deal with those challenges. However, what was perhaps the

      most important lesson that we learnt from the two of them was that we need to know our value and take a
      stand for ourselves.
      In the second episode, we had Dr. Piyush Tiwari (Professor of Property at University of Melbourne, Australia)
      from  the  Ph.D.  1998  batch.  While  cognitive  learning  is  encouraged  at  IGIDR  by  its  renowned  faculties,  Dr.
      Tiwari  made  us  realize  the  importance  of  emotive  learning  through  his  experiences.  Besides,  his  subject
      matter expertise in the field of Housing Economics allowed us to learn about something new. He also gave us

      insights on what it is like to pursue a Ph.D.
      In the third and final episode, we had Dr. Padma Sharma (Economist at Federal Reserve Bank of Kansas City)
      from  the  M.Sc.  2006  batch.  She  gave  a  small  presentation  of  her  work  that  she  had  done  at  the  Federal
      Reserve Bank of Kansas City. After the presentation, she gave her thoughts on what it is like to pursue a Ph.D.
      abroad and the challenges that one may face. She also gave us an approach of how to go about it. Her positive
      attitude and willingness to help was a huge boost for us.
      All in all, it was an absolute pleasure to hear from such eminent personalities. In a world where online classes

      have become the new norm, the way our guests got nostalgic when talking about their campus life and what
      they  liked  the  most  about  it  made  us  realize  what  we  are  missing  out  on.  Having  interactions  with  such
      people gives us motivation to aim high and work harder to achieve our goals.

                                                                                                                 43]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[KAAWISH : A BEACON OF HOPE
















      Kaawish  is  a  student-led  initiative  at  whose  heart  lies  the  belief  in  giving  back  to  society.  The  idea  for
      Kaawish was conceived as a token of gratitude for the non-teaching staff at IGIDR, considering all that they
      do for us. During its inception, all of us volunteers held multiple meetings with the parents to understand
      exactly what they wanted out of these sessions. Some of the main concerns voiced at these meetings were
      improvement in English, strengthening basics, and invigorating interest in academics for the kids. We had
      students  from  the  age  of  5  to  16.  All  the  volunteers  constantly  ensured  that  the  sessions  do  not  become

      monotonous for the kids. For instance, instead of just teaching out of a book for the entire class, we would
      dedicate some time to teach them ABACUS and Vedic mathematics to improve their analytical thinking or
      watch informative English clips and would read storybooks to improve their comprehension of the language
      in the other half of the class.




































      We would also teach them common salutations, how to introduce themselves, and soft skills in general. At the

      end of all this, we would have a 30- minute activity session. They would be given a choice to participate in
      origami making, dance classes, sports sessions, or drawing classes.


      Kaawish started with an idea and a few curious minds in the IGIDR common room and it has been more than
      a year now that it has successfully brought at least some amount of happiness in the lives of many - both
      volunteers and kids alike. It is a sphere where you do not just give back to society but


                                                                                                                 44]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[also learn some of the very beautiful aspects of life. Here, it is not just about teaching a kid allotted to
          you  but  having  the  responsibility  that  the  kids  take  away  some  valuable  lessons  from  that  1-1.5  hour
          class. We remember celebrating International Women's Day together where the students took part in
          various activities to commemorate the immense contribution of women in our society. We, at KAAWISH,

          do not consider gender equality or the journey towards it as a single-day formality. At each step, we
          tried  to  ensure  that  the  gender  stereotype  was  broken  and  along  with  the  kids,  we  all  walk  towards
          gender equality and a better tomorrow. As we celebrated Women’s Day, we were again reminded of our
          duties as students and also as fellow citizens.
                                                                  However,  fortune  had  some  other  plans.  Only
                                                                  when we thought things were in place, we had
                                                                  to  stop  Kaawish  classes  as  Covid  guidelines

                                                                  came into force. All the volunteers had to return
                                                                  to their homes. It was a heartbreaking moment
                                                                  for  all  of  us  and  we  vowed  to  resume  things
                                                                  once we are back at the institute again. As time
                                                                  went on, the scale of the pandemic became more

                                                                  and  more  clear  to  us,  and  going  back  was
                                                                  becoming  more  and  more  uncertain.  So,  by
                                                                  September,  we  decided  to  wait  no  more  and
                                                                  planned  to  resume  the  classes  but  this  time
                                                                  things were different. Instead of the face-to-face
                                                                  classes,  we  had  with  the  kids  back  in  the  good
                                                                  old days, the mode of teaching and learning was

                                                                  now online.
        So sadly, we had to do away with the activity sessions but it was very inspiring for us to see the interest

        students had in the classes even without them. The main problem we faced in the online mode was that of
        connectivity  which  hampered  the  smooth  functioning  of  a  class.  It  was  also  very  difficult  to  hold  the
        attention of a kid and make sure that they are understanding whatever we are telling them when we are
        sitting  so  far  away.  However,  we  found  that  things  are  most  important  to  have  during  these  classes  -
        patience  and  empathy.  Patience  is  important  to  keep  on  trying  and  never  give  up  on  the  learning

        outcomes and empathy helps oneself to relate with the unfortunate situation that a kid locked down from
        the  world  of  school,  friends,  and  playground  finds  herself  in.  But  still,  we  are  thankful  for  the
        advancement of technology that enables us to interact with them from across the country and talk to each
        other and learn together. From the first day, we have strived to stick to our motive and not let the
        obstacles  overpower  our  determination  of  creating  impact.  Although  the  problems  of  connectivity  and
        arranging a suitable time slot has been a nagging issue in the past few months for all of us - students and
        volunteers alike, yet the continuing enthusiasm of students to attend the classes even in an online mode

        made us relieve from all the troubles the pandemic has brought in. Despite all the hurdles, the students
        are making good progress and we are confident that this initiative will gather more momentum once we
        can shift back to the offline classes hopefully in the near future.


        Kaawish is like a sapling which the IGIDR family planted and nourished together and it grew despite all
        the adversities, giving back more than it takes. It inspires to grow and embodies all the values of IGIDR.

        We, as members of the Kaawish family, hope that it passes on across generations and grows into a big tree
        under whose shade every student of IGIDR gets inspired and learns to grow together.

                                                                                                                 45]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[NOSTALGIA









                                    CAMPUS | HOSTEL | MUMBAI


















        "It has been a year since I've left IGIDR and I've come to realize that, what seemed to be daily mundane
       activities during my stay at IGIDR, is what I miss the most now. Running from the hostel to make it in time
         for the 9.30 AM class only to sleep through most of it; sitting outside the cafeteria, chatting away with
      friends, eating my favourite breakfast - medu vada and cold coffee; spending the entire evening playing TT,
      carrom and badminton in the recreation center; staying up late on exam nights and meeting up with friends
                                             after dinner for a cup of chai.
       Of course there were the special occasions - festival celebrations with everyone on campus, the sports and
     cultural week events which we took quite seriously to be honest, those rare feasts at the Director's bungalow,
         that extra stressful week before placements and birthday celebrations that lasted till wee hours of the
                                                        morning.
         All in all, the time that I've spent at IGIDR has been an experience of a lifetime. The place has given me
      memories that I'll always hold close to my heart and friends who have now become an indispensable part of
                                                        my life. "
                                                            "                                   - Namrata Sen
                                                                                                ( M.Sc. 2018-20)




                                                      "IGIDR, a place that beholds countless memories, and has given

                                                        me life-long friends. Wish I could've had the opportunity to
                                                      relive the journey yet again! Right from the first semester to the
                                                       last, every memory will be treasured. Be it the sleepless nights
                                                         before the submission of micro assignments, the ceaseless
                                                       dining hall conversations, the night before time series exams,
                                                        the fifth-floor balcony, the cold coffee, the 'anda-maggi ', the
                                                        cats, the leopards, or the red square, will forever be etched in
                                                       my heart. IGIDR and its people will be sorely missed. Hope our
                                                             paths cross soon and get the closure we deserve!"


                                                                                                    - Ipsita Das
                                                                                                    ( M.Sc. 2018-20)





                                                                                                                 46]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA["Apart from the library with subscriptions to most
          leading journals, the 24x7 computer centre
        allowing flexible study hours and the academic
      infrastructure in general, the thing that struck me
         the most on the first few days was the sports
      facilities on campus. Ranging from carrom and TT
       to cricket and volleyball, there's hardly any sport
        that isn't played over here. What made it even
         more fun was that students, professors, non-
       teaching staff and children would all play side by
      side. This feeling of living in a community and not
        just a hostel is something that separates IGIDR
           from most other academic institutions."

                                   - Sasmit Dutta

                                     ( M.Sc. 2018-20)









                                                                    "The magic of IGIDR is hard to put in a small
                                                                     paragraph. Living in IGIDR campus is like a
                                                                 celebration. Where else can you find yourself being
                                                                   pampered like this. Every person here is equal,
                                                                    whether it be a teaching staff, student or non-
                                                                  teaching staff. We all are a part of this small loving
                                                                  family. We eat, play and celebrate every occasion
                                                                  together. I can never forget how even though the
                                                                  pressure of exams and assignments kept us awake
                                                                  at night,  Nagori chai at 4AM just after you clicked

                                                                  the submit button for your assignment was a love.
                                                                  We had one to one interactions with profs due to
                                                                  this small batch size. We used to decide ourselves
                                                                  the timing of our exams. Being up and partying all
                                                                    night. Going to bed at 4-5am and waking up at
                                                                     9:30am and rushing to classes with a cup of
                                                                      espresso shot was quite a habit.  Also our
                                                                    Wednesday biryani and Sunday dosas. We all
                                                                 complained about it but we all looked forward to it,
                                                                      Always. IGIDR is not a place. It's a feeling."



                                                                                              - Komal Baranwal
                                                                                                   ( M.Sc. 2018-20)








                                                                                                                 47]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA["In my UG course, my batch had students from different backgrounds which was apparent from their

        family income. These differences resulted in a barrier among the students which led to segregation and two
           groups in the batch. To my surprise, there used to be absolutely minimal interaction between the two
           groups. A few of the students tried to be part of the supposedly higher group but did not get adequate
            acceptance. Even my seniors told me that it had been a common phenomenon for years especially in
          Economics and English departments. For students coming from small towns (in my case, coming from a
                                    village), it feels like the college is not accepting us.
          I came to IGIDR with the same fear. However, although the students were from different backgrounds at
         IGIDR as well, nothing of that sort happened. I guess hostel accommodation for all and the small batch size
         helped to not have such a segregation. I always felt like at home and the institute had accepted me warmly.
                                        My heart keeps a special place for IGIDR. "



                                                                                - Mritunjay Kumar
                                                                                    ( M.Sc. 2018-20)









                                                                                    "एक खास जगह का आम  दन ...

        “Gar firdaus bar-rue zamin ast, hami asto, hamin asto, hamin ast.”
        I am telling you, it would not be an exaggeration to compare IGIDR           वो छोटे से सफर म  होती, ल बी

        campus to heaven. The campus is really very beautiful and people                    सी मुलाकात,
        there enhance its charm even more. This place brings back so many            वो बो र ग से ले चर म  चलती,
           memories - evening talks, night parties, sports participation,                रोचक सी कोई बात,
        watching movies with friends, festivals celebrations and what not.           वो ठहाक  संग सुरा ती, शाम क
         Life at IGIDR is not only full of thrill and enjoyment but also is a               मसाला चाय,
       great place to learn and explore. The small batch size makes the class         वो  डनर टेबल पर द  जाती,
         a family. Faculties are very approachable, and students can easily               फ़ज़ूल सी फ़ज़  राय,
        interact with them. The series of educational seminars throughout           वो 5th  लोर पर टकराते, वाद
        the year creates a suitable atmosphere for the research orientation                के  नशीले जाम,
         and the scope for the discussion on the current economic aspects.           वो  फर सवेरे जागता सूरज, वो
         Infrastructure and other facilities (badminton court, swimming                फर मु काती ढलती शाम।"
        pool, tennis court, library, computer centre, etc.) are very amazing.
        Other than academics, there are many co-curricular activities like
        sports week, cultural week, Ganesh puja, Annual day and Saraswati
        puja which makes this place even more lively. Student led initiative
        "Kaawish" (teaching IGIDR staff's children on weekends ) not only           - Shubham Singh Lodhi
                                                                                          ( M.Sc. 2018-20)
       enables we students to contribute something towards the society but
       also makes our IGIDR family more united. Certainly, these were one

         of the best years of my life with very amazing people out there. "




                                                                                                                 48]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA["IGIDR had wonderful people in it. Seniors who were
                                                        downright competitive about Dumb Charades and made
                                                         me a better player (they also helped in numerous other
                                                        ways, but this is what I will remember them for). Canteen

                                                          staff who were always up for friendly banter and sat
                                                           alongside me cheering for India in the World Cup.
                                                       Professors who stayed helpful and patient and saved many
                                                            lives when pesky doubts cropped up just around
                                                       examination season. Guard uncles who smiled and waved
                                                        and once even offered me some home-made pickle from
                                                        their lunches. And friends who I inadvertently picked up
                                                        along the way and now cannot let go of for some reason.
                                                       IGIDR was a wonderful place. Sunsets were magical when
                                                         seen from the fifth-floor balcony. Idli-sambhar always
                                                       tasted better when eaten outside the cafeteria. The library
                                                        was huge and intimidating but also cool and exciting and
                                                        at night, Khan Chacha sat at the entrance with his radio
                                                                 and smiled warmly at our tired faces.
                                                        At IGIDR, we raced around campus looking for Treasure
                                                         Hunt clues. We became obsessed with cold coffee and
                                                         nimbu pani, and had long email chains discussing the
                                                        welfare of campus cats. We stayed up late for Time Series.

                                                                   We woke up early for Time Series.
                                                        I smile because it happened. I am furious that it was torn
                                                          away from us so soon. And I am excited that there are
                                                          others out there yet to experience life in IGIDR, and
                                                         perhaps one day I can swap campus stories with them."




                                                                       - Dipanwita Ghatak

                                                                           ( M.Sc. 2018-20 )




















                                                                                                                 49]]></page></pages></Search>